Hi.
In this problem, we're going to
find an unbiased estimator
for the variance of
a random variable.
Suppose random variable X has
some unknown mean theta and
some unknown variance v. We're
going to use some i.i.d.
observations of X, X1 through
Xn, and combine these
observations to find an
estimator that will estimate
theta and v.
Now, how do you know if an
estimator's any good?
For example, here's
a bad estimator.
If I'm trying to estimate what
theta is, I could come up with
an estimator that takes in
these observations, but
ignores them, and always just
spits out zero as the estimate
for what the mean is.
So that estimator's probably
not very good.
So how do you know if an
estimator is good?
Well, there are some properties
of estimators that
are desirable to have.
One of them is for the
estimators to be unbiased.
So an estimator, capital A, of
some unknown parameter, little
a, is unbiased if the expected
value of this estimator is
equal to the parameter that
you're trying to estimate.
Remember that in general,
an estimator is a random
variable, because it's based on
some random observations.
So it won't always
be equal to.
It won't always give
you the value that
you're trying to estimate.
But if it's unbiased, you know
that on average it'll give you
the right value.
Let's practice first on the
mean, theta, and see if we can
come up with an unbiased
estimator for it.
One proposal is the
sample mean.
Let's calculate the sample mean
as the average of all of
the n i.i.d. samples
that we get.
So you take X1, add up all
the Xi's and divide by n.
And we'll call that Mn.
So in order verify that this
is in fact unbiased, all we
have to do is calculate the
expected value of Mn and
verify that it's
equal to theta.
The expected value of Mn, in
order to calculate it, we'll
rely on linearity
of expectations.
The first we can do is we
could pull out a 1/n.
And then in order to calculate
the expectation of the sum by
linearity again, that is
equal to the sum of the
expectations.
And so, what we get is it's
expectation of X1 plus all the
way through expectation of Xn.
Because X1 through Xn are all
i.i.d. observations of X, they
all have the same mean,
which is theta.
And so it's 1/n times n copies
of theta, which gives you that
the expectation of Mn is
in fact equal to theta.
And so we've shown that
this is an unbiased
estimator of the mean.
Now let's try to take that and
see if we can find an unbiased
estimator for the variance v.
And here is one proposal.
Let's let Sn hat squared be
equal to this expression.
Let's see what we're
doing here.
We're taking each sample, Xi,
subtracting the sample mean,
squaring it, and then taking
some sort of average of those.
And this seems like it may be a
good choice, because this is
kind of like what a variance
calculation does.
You take the square deviations
from the mean, and take some
sort of average of those.
So let's see if this is
actually correct.
And in order to do that, we'll
do the same thing that we did
for the mean, which is we'll
calculate the expectation of
Sn hat squared and verify
that it's equal to v.
First, let's try to simplify
this expression a little bit.
So we can expand this square.
And we'll get Xi squared minus
2Xi times Mn plus Mn squared.
And next, let's distribute
this summation.
So we'll split it up into three
different summations.
The first one adds up
all the Xi squares.
The second one adds up
all of the Xi's.
So we can pull out the Mn
outside of the summation,
because Mn does not depend
on the summation index i.
And lastly, we have a summation
of Mn squared.
And just like for this
case, Mn squared also
doesn't depend on i.
So we just have n copies
of Mn squared.
Now let's look at this middle
expression here.
We know that the sum of the Xi's
is actually just equal to
n times Mn.
So let's substitute
that in to try to
simplify this even more.
So the sum of the Xi's is equal
to n times Mn, so we
have 2 times Mn times n times
Mn, which gives us two times n
times Mn squared for that.
And now we also added
n times Mn squared.
And so what we are
left with is just
minus n times Mn squared.
So we simplified this expression
a little bit.
And now if we were to try to
calculate the expected value,
we know that we're going to have
to rely on linearity of
expectations again.
And if we look forward, we can
see that what we're going to
have to calculate eventually
is the expectation of Xi
squared and the expectation
of Mn squared.
So let's calculate
those first.
What is the expectation
of Xi squared?
The expectation of Xi squared,
we can write that as the
variance of Xi plus
the expectation
of Xi quantity squared.
Now, what is the
variance of Xi?
The variance of Xi is v. What
is the expectation of Xi?
The expectation of
Xi is theta.
And we square that.
So we get that this is equal
to v plus theta squared.
What about the expectation
of Mn squared?
The expectation of Mn squared
we can do a similar thing.
And this is equal to the
variance of Mn plus the
expectation of Mn quantity
squared.
But we don't know what the
variance of Mn is yet, so
let's try to calculate
what that is.
The variance of Mn is the
variance of the sample mean.
So it's the variance of 1/n
times the sum of all the Xi's.
We know that 1/n is just some
constant, and when we pull it
out of the variance, we
have to square it.
So we get 1/n squared times this
variance, the variance of
sum of the Xi's.
But because the Xi's are
independent, the variance of
the sum is actually equal to
the sum of the variance.
So what we get is the variance
of X1 plus all the way through
the variance of Xn.
All of these variances are equal
to v. And so we get n
times v divided by n squared.
And that gives us v/n.
Now, what is the expectation
of Mn?
Expectation of Mn, when we
calculated it earlier, we saw
that this actually is
equal to theta.
And so we can fill
this in now.
The variance of Mn is
equal to v over n.
And the expectation
of Mn is theta.
And you square that, you
get theta squared.
So now we know both of
these expectations.
So let's calculate the actual
expected value of this
estimator, Sn hat squared.
So like we alluded to earlier,
it's going to use linearity of
expectations.
So the 1 over n minus 1,
we can pull that out.
By linearity, we have that this
is just the sum of the
expectation of all
the Xi squares.
And then we have n times the
expectation of Mn squared.
We still have the 1
over n minus 1.
We calculated the value of
expectation of Xi squared.
It's equal to v plus
theta squared.
That doesn't depend on i, so we
just have n copies of that.
So it's n times v plus n
times theta squared.
We know also the expectation
of Mn squared.
It's v/n plus theta squared.
We multiply that by n, and
we get v plus n squared.
And we subtract, so we
get minus v minus
10 times theta squared.
These cancel, n times theta
squared cancel out.
You get nv minus v, which is n
minus 1 times v. The n minus 1
cancels out with the
1 over n minus 1.
And so in the end, you get that
this is in fact equal to
the expectation of the
estimator, is equal to v. And
that shows that this estimator
is in fact an unbiased
estimator of this variance, v.
So I hope that was helpful.
And we'll see you next time.