In this segment, we will look
at the famous example, which
was posed by Comte de Buffon,
a French naturalist back in
the 18th century.
And it marks the beginning of a
subject that is known as the
subject of geometric
probability.
The problem is pretty simple.
We have the infinite plane.
And we draw lines that are
parallel to each other.
And they are spaced
apart d units.
So this distance here is d.
And the same for all
the other lines.
We take a needle that has
a certain length, l.
And we throw it at random
on the plane.
So the needle might fall
this way, so that it
doesn't cross any line.
Or it might fall this way, so
that it ends up crossing one
of the lines.
If the needle is long enough, it
might actually even end up
crossing two of the lines.
But we will make the assumption
that the length of
the needle is less than
the distance between
two adjacent lines.
So that we're going to have
either this configuration or
that configuration.
So in this setting, we're
interested in the question of
how likely is it that the needle
is going to intersect
one of the lines if the
needle is thrown
completely at random?
We will answer this question.
And we will proceed
as follows.
First, we need to model the
probabilistic experiment
mathematically.
That is, we need to define an
appropriate sample space,
define some relevant random
variables, choose an
appropriate probability law,
identify the event of
interest, and then
calculate it.
Let us see what it takes to
describe a typical outcome of
the experiment.
Suppose that the needle
fell this way.
So that the nearest line
is the one above.
And let us mark here the
center of the needle.
One quantity of interest is this
vertical distance between
the needle and the
nearest line.
Let us call this quantity x.
We're using here a lowercase x,
because we're dealing with
a numerical value in one
particular outcome of the
experiment.
But we think of this x as being
the realization of a
certain random variable that we
we'll denote by capital X.
What else does it take to
describe the needle?
Suppose that the needle had
fallen somewhere, so that it
is at the same vertical distance
from the nearest
line, but it has an orientation
of this kind.
This orientation compared to
that one should make a
difference.
Because when it falls that way,
it's more likely that
it's going to cut the next line,
as opposed to this case.
So the angle that the needle
is making with the parallel
lines should also be relevant.
So let us give a name to
that particular angle.
So let's extend that
line until it
crosses one of the lines.
And let us give a name to this
angle, and call it theta.
So if I tell you x and theta,
you know how far away the
needle is from the nearest line,
and at what angle it is.
It looks like these are two
useful variables to describe
the outcome of the experiment.
So let us try to working
with these.
So our model is going to involve
two random variables,
defined the way we discussed
just now.
What is the range of these
random variables?
Since we took x to be the
distance from the nearest
line, and the lines are d units
apart, this means that x
is going to be somewhere
between 0 and d over 2.
How about theta?
So the needle makes two angles
with the parallel line.
It's this angle, and the
complementary one.
Which one do we take?
Well, we use the convention that
theta is defined as the
acute angle that the direction
of the needle is
making with the lines.
So that theta will vary over a
range from 0 to pi over 2.
And our sample space for the
experiment will be the set of
all pairs of x and theta that
satisfy these two conditions.
These will be the possible
x's and thetas.
Having defined the sample space,
next we need to define
a probability law.
At this point, we do not want
to make any arbitrary
assumptions.
We only have the words
completely at random to go by.
But what do these words mean?
We will interpret them to
mean that there are
no preferred x values.
So that's all x values are, in
some sense, equally likely.
So we're going to assume
that X is a
uniform random variable.
Since it is uniform, it's going
to be a constant over
this range.
And in order to integrate to 1,
that constants will have to
be 2 over d.
And we understand that the PDF
of X is 0 outside that range.
Similarly, for theta that we
do not want to assume that
some orientations are more
likely than other
orientations.
So we will again assume
a uniform probability
distribution.
And therefore that PDF must be
equal to 2 over pi for thetas
over this particular range.
So far we have specified the
marginal PDF's for each one of
the two random variables.
How about their joint PDF?
In order to have a complete
model, we need to have a joint
PDF in our hands.
Here, we're going to make the
assumption that X and THETA
are independent of each other.
And in that case, the joint
PDF is determined by just
taking the product of
the marginal PDF's.
So the joint PDF is going
to be equal to 4
divided by pi times d.
By this point, we have
completely specified the
probabilistic model.
We have made some assumptions,
which you might
even consider arbitrary.
But these assumptions are
a reasonable attempt at
capturing the idea that
the needle is thrown
completely at random.
This completes the subjective
part, the modeling part.
The next step is much
more streamlined.
There's not going to
be any choices.
We just need to consider the
event of interest, express it
in terms of the random variables
that we have in our
hands, and then you use the
probability model that we have
to calculate the probability
of this particular event.
So let us identify the
event of interest.
When will the needle intersect
the nearest line?
This will depend on
the following.
We can look at the vertical
extent of the needle.
By vertical extent, I
mean the following.
Let's see how far the needle
goes in the vertical
direction, which is the length
of this green segment here.
In this example, the vertical
extent of the needle is less
than the distance from
the next line.
And we do not have
an intersection.
If the figure was something like
this, the vertical extent
of the needle would have been
that, but x would have been
just this little segment.
The vertical extent
is bigger than x.
And the needle intersects
the line.
So we have an intersection if
and only if the vertical
extent, which is this vertical
green segment, is larger than
the distance x.
Or, equivalently, if x is less
than the vertical extent.
So we will have an intersection
if x is less than
or equal to the vertical
extent of the needle.
Now how big is this
vertical extent?
Let's use some trigonometry
here.
This angle here is theta.
So this angle here
is also theta.
Here we have a right triangle.
And the hypotenuse of this
triangle is l over 2.
This angle is theta.
Therefore this vertical segment
is equal to l over 2
times the sine theta.
So this is the geometrical
condition that describes the
event that the needle intersects
the nearest line.
And all we need to do now is to
calculate the probability
of this event.
So here's what we have so far.
This is the picture that we
had before, but drawn in a
somewhat nicer way.
This is the joint PDF that
we decided upon.
And we wish to calculate the
probability of this particular
event, that is less than or
equal to l over 2 sine THETA.
How do we calculate the
probability of an event that
has to do with two
random variables?
What we do is we take the joint
PDF, which in our case
is 4 over pi d, and integrate
it over the set of x's and
thetas for which the
PDF is non-zero.
So it's only going to
be over x's and
thetas in those ranges.
And also only for those x theta
pairs for which the
event occurs.
So what are these pairs?
This event can occur with
any choice of theta.
So theta is free to vary
from 0 to pi over 2.
How about x?
For this event to occur, x
can be anything that is
non-negative, as long as
it is less than or
equal to this number.
So the upper limit of this
integration is going to be l
over 2 times sine theta.
And all we need to do now is to
evaluate this double integral.
Let's start with the
inner integral.
Because we're just integrating a
constant, the inner integral
evaluates to the constant we're
integrating, which is 4
times pi d, times the length
of the interval over which
we're integrating, which
is l over 2 sine theta.
And now we need to carry
out the outer integral.
Let us pull out the constants,
which is this 4 with
this 2 give us 2.
We have 2l over pi d.
And then the integral from 0
to pi over 2 of sine theta.
Now the integral of sine theta
is minus cosine theta.
And we need to evaluate this
at 0 and pi over 2.
This turns out to
be equal to 1.
So the final result
is 2l over pi d.
And this is the final answer
to the problem that we have
been considering.
And now, a curious thought.
Suppose that you do not know
what the number pi is.
And all you have in your hands
is your floor, lines drawn on
your floor, and the needle.
And you do know the length
between adjacent
lines on your floor.
And you do know your length
of your needle.
How can you figure out
the number pi?
Take your needle.
Throw it at random,
a million times.
And count the frequency with
which the needle ends up
crossing the line.
If you believe that
probabilities can be
interpreted as frequencies, the
frequency that you observe
gives you a good estimate
of this probability.
So it gives you a
good estimate of
this particular number.
And if you know the length of
your needle, and of the
distance between the different
lines, you can use the
estimate of that number to
determine the value of pi.
This is a so-called Monte
Carlo method, which uses
simulation to evaluate
experimentally the value, in
this case, of the
constant, pi.
Of course, for pi, we have
much better ways of
calculating it.
But there are many applications
in engineering
and in physics where certain
quantities are hard to calculate.
But they can be calculated using
a trick of this kind of
by simulation.
Here's a typical situation.
Consider the unit cube.
And for simplicity, I'm only
taking a cube in two
dimensions.
But in general, think of the
unit cube in n dimensions
which is an object that's
has unit volume.
Inside that unit cube, there is
a complicated subset, which
is described maybe by some very
complicated formulas.
And you want to calculate
the volume of
this complicated subset.
The description of the subset
is so complicated that using
integration, multiple integrals,
and calculus is
practically impossible.
What can you do?
What you can do is to start
throwing, at random, points
inside that unit cube.
So you throw points.
Some fall inside.
Some fall outside.
You count the frequency with
which is the points happened
to be inside your set.
And as long as you're throwing
the points uniformly over the
cube, then the probability of
your complicated set is going
to be the volume of that set.
You estimated a probability by
counting the frequency with
which you get points
into that set.
And so, by using these observed
frequencies, you can
estimate the volume of a sets,
something that might be very
difficult to do through other
numerical methods.
It turns out that these days
physicists and many engineers
use methods of this kind quite
often, and in many important
applications.