Hi.
In this problem, we're throwing
a dart at a circle.
And the circle has
radius of r.
And what we assume is that
we always hit the target.
So whatever we throw, the dart
always lands somewhere within
the circle.
And so we don't miss completely
and hit out here.
And the other thing we assume is
that all points within the
circle are equally likely.
All right.
So that's the set
up the problem.
And what we're asked to do
is to come up with some
distributions, some densities.
And the first thing that
we'll do is we'll
define two random variables.
All right.
So we'll define random
variable X to be the
x-coordinate of where we hit
on the target and random
variable Y to be the
y-coordinate.
So now we have these two
random variables.
And the first part of the
problem is to calculate what
the joint PDF is.
So what is the joint
PDF of X and Y?
Well, in this case, it's not so
bad, because we are told to
assume that all points
are equally likely.
So what does that mean?
That means that within this
circle, which is where the
target is, it's uniformly
distributed.
So all points are
equally likely.
So all we have to do now to find
what this joint PDF is is
to calculate what this area is
and take 1 over the area.
So it's 1 over the area.
And as you know, the area of
the circle is pi r squared.
So it's just 1 over pi r squared
when you are within
the circle.
And what is the equation
of a circle?
The equation of a circle
is x squared plus y
squared equals r squared.
So we're centering the
coordinate system at 0.00.
That's where the circle
is centered.
So we lie within this circle
when x squared plus y squared
is less than or equal
to r squared.
And we always hit the target.
So we never fall outside
of this circle.
So within the circle, it's
uniformly distributed and the
normalization or the scaling
factor is 1 over the area.
And outside, it's 0.
All right.
Now, the second part asks us
to find the conditional
distribution of X given
Y So what is the
distribution of X given Y?
Well, the distribution
of X given Y--
we know we can calculate that
from taking the joint PDF of X
and Y and dividing by the
marginal of Y. OK.
So first, let's calculate what
the marginal of y is.
The marginal of y--
when you calculate a marginal,
remember, it's just a matter
of taking the joint and
integrating out to the
variable that you don't
want any more.
So in this case, we're
integrating out x.
And in general, you integrate
from x equals minus infinity
to infinity.
But in this case, we need to be
careful what the limits are
and only integrate when
the limits are valid.
So for now, let's just write
minus infinity to infinity.
And we'll fill that in.
So we know that the joint PDF
is just 1 over the area, 1
over pi r squared.
Now, when is this joint
PDF actually valid?
All right.
So now let's fix some value
of y that we want.
Let's say it's this
one right here.
This is the value of y.
Well, given that that's the
value of y, what range of x is
this joint PDF valid?
Well, it's valid for the range
of x that falls within this
band here, from here to here.
Now, what are these
two values?
Well, if y is here and the
radius is r and we know that
the equation of the circle is
x squared plus y squared
equals r squared, then we know
that this point has to equal
the square root of r squared
minus y squared.
That's the value of x that
corresponds with
that value of y.
And then similarly, here we have
minus square root of r
squared minus y squared.
So that's the range of Xs
for that value of y.
So that actually becomes the
limits of our integration.
And the good thing
is that this is
just a constant, right?
There's no y in here.
And so we can just
pull that out.
And really, it just becomes an
integral of a constant or an
integral 1 from minus square
root of r squared minus y
squared 2 square root of r
squared minus y squared.
So it actually is just going
to be 2 square root of r
squared minus y squared
over pi r squared.
And again, this is valid only
for y from minus r to r.
And it's 0 otherwise.
So why is that?
It's because no matter what, y
can only go as high as the
radius in either direction.
So y is bounded between
minus r and r.
And so another way to look at
this graphically is you're
just taking this joint PDF and
squishing it to the y-axis.
And so the only parts that will
get nonzero contributions
are the ones from
r to minus r.
And note that although the
original joint distribution
was uniform--
we assumed so--
when you take the marginal of
y, the marginal of y is not
uniform, right?
Notice that it actually
depends on y here.
And it varies depending
on what y is.
And it turns out that it will
be largest when y is 0 and
smallest when y is
r or minus r.
Why is that?
Because when you squish this,
you get more contribution when
you're at y equals 0.
It's more likely for y to be 0
because there are a lot more
corresponding Xs that pair
with that y equals 0.
And when you're all the way up
here, there are very few other
Xs that will pair with that.
OK.
So we found the marginal
distribution of Y. And now all
that's left to do is to
calculate out what this
quotient is.
So we have the joint
distribution.
And we have the marginal.
So let's just calculate out
what the conditional
distribution is.
OK.
So the numerator is just
1 over the area.
And the denominator is this--
2 times square root of r squared
minus y squared over
pi r squared.
And of course, we can do
some cancellations and
simplifications.
But the first thing we want to
do is, as always, to check
what range this is
a valid for.
So the numerator is the
joint distribution.
And that's valid for any
x and y pairs that
fall within the circle.
And the bottom is valid
for any y that is
between minus r and r.
And so what this tells us is
that this is in fact valid for
any pairs of x and y that
fall within this circle.
So it's valid for x squared plus
y squared less than or
equal to r squared.
And outside of it, it's 0.
And what we can do is simplify
this a little bit, right?
Because this will cancel
out with the top.
And what we're left with is just
1 over 2 times the square
root of r squared
minus y squared.
And note here now that for any
given conditioning on Y being
at some value little y, this
conditional density of X no
longer depends on x.
So it is in fact uniform
along a certain range.
So another way to write this
range that is maybe a little
more explicit is that y has to
be between negative r and r.
So that's what you're
conditioning on.
You know that y can only
be these values.
And then given that Y is that
little y, then this is true
for some range of x.
So given that y is some value,
you know that x can only go
from minus y squared minus y
squared to the positive square
root of y squared minus y
squared minus square root of r
squared minus y squared less
than x less than equal to
square root of r squared
minus y squared.
So it's doing the analogous
calculation as we did earlier.
And so what we see is that it
is in fact uniform, right?
Because it doesn't
depend on x.
And why is that?
It's because when you take
conditioning on Y being some
little value it's, as we talked
about, it's as if
you're taking a slice
along that value.
And now remember that the
original joint distribution
was uniform.
So it was like a round
cake that was flat.
And now you take a slice of that
cake, a horizontal slice,
at some particular value of y.
Well, when you take that slice,
then you know that, if
you can imagine it coming
out of the board, this
distribution of X will
also be still flat.
So the distribution of X
will still be uniform.
And that's what you get here.
So it's interesting
that the original
distribution is uniform.
But when you marginalize it
and take the marginal
distribution of Y, you get
something that is not uniform,
where it depends on y.
And by symmetry, you can say
that when you marginalize out
y and take the marginal
distribution of just X, you
will also see that the marginal
distribution of X is
also not uniform.
But when you then calculate the
conditional distribution,
you get a uniform distribution
back again.
And that's because you're taking
this slice, right?
The reason is that, depending on
where the slice is, you get
a longer slice.
And because of that, the
marginal distribution becomes
higher closer to the axis
and smaller when
you go to the extremes.
But as long as you know and you
condition on just taking
some slice, within
that slice, the
distribution will be uniform.
OK.
So this is just a slightly
different kind of joint
distribution with a
circular shape.
Mostly we've been dealing more
with kind of angular
distributions.
And so you can see that even
with circular distributions,
you get something.
You can still apply the same
kind of methodologies and
tools to get the answers
that you want.
All right.
So I hope that was helpful.
And we'll see you next time.