Hi.
In this session, we're going
to work on a drill problem
to get some more practice
working with Poisson processes.
So remember, a
Poisson process is
a process that models
how things arrive.
And the important
parameter is lambda,
which is the arrival rate,
the number of arrivals
per unit time.
And another important
factor to remember
for this problem is that when
you consider disjoint time
intervals, whatever happens
in these two disjoint time
intervals is independent.
So here in this
problem, we have trains
that are crossing this bridge.
And we're told that the
trains arrive at this bridge
according to a Poisson
process at a rate of three
trains per day.
So that doesn't mean
that there's exactly
three trains per day.
It just means that
in some sense,
on average, three
trains come every day.
But the number of trains on
each day is actually random.
And an important
formula to remember
is that of a Poisson
distribution, which tells you
the probability of having k
arrivals over a period of tau
days.
And that's equal to e
to the minus lambda tau,
times lambda tau to
the k over k factorial.
OK, so the first
part of this problem
asks us to find what is
the probability that you'll
have no trains arriving on
days one, two, and three,
supposing that there's a train
that arrived on day zero.
So the information
that we're given
is that there's a train
that arrived on day zero.
And then we're asked to
find a probability related
to days one, two, and three.
So what we should remember is
that disjoint time intervals
are independent.
So whatever happened
on day zero is
independent of what happens
on days one, two, and three.
So we can actually just
forget about the fact
that a train
arrived on day zero,
and just focus on what happens
on days one, two, and three.
So what we really
want is just, what's
the probability of
0 trains in 3 days.
Days one, two, and
three cover 3 days.
And if we just now
apply this formula,
we can know exactly
how to find that.
So now k is 0, tau is
3, and lambda is 3,
given by the problem.
So what we get is e to
the minus lambda tau.
Lambda is 3, tau is 3, so
that's e to the minus 9,
times lambda tau is 9, to the
k, which is 0, over 0 factorial.
So 9 to the 0 is 1.
0 factorial is 1.
So all you're left with
is just e to the minus 9.
And that is the probability of
having no trains in three days.
So just remember that disjoint
time intervals are independent,
and don't get tripped
up over information
that actually is irrelevant.
Now, part (b)--
we're asked to find,
what is the probability that
if a train arrives on day
zero that it takes more than
three days for the next train
to arrive?
Well, if you think
about that, really, it's
asking the exact same
thing as part (a),
because the event that
the next train takes
more than three days
is exactly the same
as there being no trains
in the next three days.
So in fact, this is exactly
equal to the same probability
that we calculated in part
(a)-- e to the minus 9.
Part (c) now says,
what's the probability
that you have no trains on days
one and two-- the first two
days-- but four trains
on the fourth day?
OK, so now this question
involves days one and two
and day four.
So again, let's
rely on this fact,
that disjoint time
intervals are independent.
So we can actually
calculate the probability
of no trains in
the first two days,
and then calculate
the probability
of four trains on
the fourth day,
and combine them, because
they're independent.
So the probability
that we're looking for
is 0 trains in days one and
two, and 4 trains on day four.
But because this
is independent, we
can actually calculate the
probability of this first part,
the probability of
the second part,
and multiply them together.
So what's the probability of
no trains in days one and two?
Well, that is just,
again, probability
of no arrivals in a
duration of length 2,
which again, we can calculate
using this formula, where
k is 0 and tau is now 2.
So what we get is e to
the minus lambda tau--
lambda tau here
is minus 6-- times
6 to the 0 over 0 factorial.
So that's the first
part, the probability
of 0 trains in days one and two.
Now, what's the probability
of 4 trains in day four?
Well, we want now
the probability
of 4 arrivals in a
duration of length 1,
which we can, again, use
this formula to calculate.
That's going to be e to
the minus lambda tau.
Now, tau is 1, and k we
want to be equal to 4.
So lambda tau is 3.
And we want lambda tau-- 3 to
the fourth over 4 factorial.
And now, that is just
going to be equal
to-- we can pull out an
e to the minus 9 here.
This 6 to the 0 over 0
factorial is just one.
And then the rest of it is just
times 3 to the fourth over 4
factorial.
We can simplify it
if we wanted to.
So again, that
relied on this fact
that disjoint time
intervals are independent,
and that's an
important tool to have.
The next and last
part of this problem
asks us for the probability that
it'll take more than two days
for the fifth train to arrive.
So we want the probability
that more than 2 days
for the fifth train.
Well, what's another
way of saying that?
In order to take more than
2 days for the fifth train
to arrive, that's
exactly the same
as saying there was no
more than four trains
in the first 2 days.
So we've transformed this into
something about the number
of days until a certain arrival
to the number of arrivals
within a certain number of days,
because if you have no more
than 4 trains in
the first 2 days,
then the fifth train could
not have arrived until after 2
days.
Obviously, you can calculate
using either of these.
In this way, you would have
to know something about
the distribution of
the fifth arrival time,
and calculate the probability
that being greater than 2,
which you could do.
Alternatively, you could
also re-frame it in terms
of the probability of having
no more than a certain number
of arrivals within
the first 2 days.
So let's do it, in this case,
using the second method.
We want, now, the probability
of no more than 4 trains
in the first 2 days.
Well, that's the same as the
probability of there beings 0
trains in the first 2 days,
plus the probability of being 1
train, and so on, all
the way up to 4 trains,
because you can't have both 1
train in the first 2 days and 2
trains in the first 2 days.
So those probabilities
you can just add up.
And so it turns out that it's
just equal to the probability
of the sum for k equals 0 up to
4 of the probability of having
exactly k arrivals in 2 days.
So the probability of having
k arrivals in 2 days is just e
to the minus lambda tau.
Lambda is 3, still.
Tau is 2 now, so it's
e to the minus 6,
times 6 to the k
over k factorial.
And now we can
simplify this somewhat,
and actually calculate out
what the summation equals.
We pull out e to the minus 6.
Then we get 6 to the
0 over 0 factorial,
plus 6 to the first
power over 1 factorial,
plus all the way to 6 to
the fourth over 4 factorial.
And now the last part is, we
can actually calculate out what
that number is equal to.
And it turns out it's equal
to 115 times e to the minus 6.
OK, so this last problem
just demonstrates that
there's multiple ways of
framing any particular problem.
You can frame it in
terms of arrival times,
or you can frame it in terms
of the number of arrivals.
And depending on the situation,
maybe one way is easier than
the other one.
OK, so that was just a quick
drill problem for Poisson
processes.
And I hope that was helpful,
and see you next time.