You build a local communication
network consisting
of routers, computers,
and some hard-wired links
that connect them.
However, its link has
a small probability
of being nonfunctional
because of a hardware failure.
Assuming that failures
at different lengths
happen independently,
how likely is it
that the message from
router A will still
be able to reach your computer?
Suppose now that you received
notice that one of the routers
is down.
Given this information,
how would you
update the probability that
the message from router A
will still be able to
reach your computer?
By the end of this
unit, you will
be able to answer
questions of this type
by using the concept of
conditional probability
and by giving a precise
meaning to the concept
of independent failures.