Hi.
Today we're going to do another
fun problem that
involves rolling [of]
two dice.
So if you guys happen to
frequent casinos, this problem
might be really useful
for you.
I'm just kidding.
But in all seriousness, this
problem is a good problem,
because it's going to remind
us how and when to use the
discrete uniform law.
Don't worry, I'll review
what that says.
And it's also going to exercise
your understanding of
conditional probability.
So quick recap.
The discrete uniform law says
that when your sample space is
discrete, and when the outcomes
in your sample space
are equally likely, then to
compute the probability of any
event A, you can simply count
the number of outcomes in A
and divide it by the total
number of possible outcomes.
OK, so coming back
to our problem.
The problem statement tells
us that we roll two fair
six-sided [dice].
And it also tells us that each
one of the 36 possible
outcomes is assumed to
be equally likely.
So you know alarm bell should
be going off in your head.
Our sample space is
clearly discrete.
And it says explicitly that all
outcomes are equally likely.
So clearly, we can use the
discrete uniform law.
And again, this is helpful
because it reduces a problem
of computing probabilities
to a problem of counting.
OK, and before we go any
further, I just want to review
what this graph is plotting.
You've seen it a few times, but
just to clarify, on one
axis, we're plotting the outcome
of the first die roll,
and on the second axis,
we're plotting [the]
outcome of the second
die roll.
So if you got a 4 on your first
die, and you get a 1 on
your second die, that
corresponds to this point over
4 and up 1.
OK, so part (a) asks us to
find the probability that
doubles are rolled.
So let's use some shorthand.
We're going to let D be the
event that doubles are rolled.
And we want to compute
the probability of D.
I argue before we can use the
discrete uniform law.
So if we apply that, we just
get the number of outcomes
that comprise the event "doubles
rolled", divided by
36, because there are 36
possible outcomes, which you
can see just by counting
the dots in this graph.
Six possible outcomes for the
first die, six possible
outcomes for the second die.
That's how you--
6 times 6 is 36.
So I've been assuming this
entire time that you know what
doubles are.
For those of you who don't know,
doubles is essentially
when that number on the first
die matches the number on the
second die.
So this outcome here 1-1 is
part of the event "doubles
rolled." Similarly, 2-2, 3-3,
4-4, 5-5, and 6-6--
these six points comprise the
event "doubles rolled."
So we can go ahead and
put 6 over 36,
which is equal to 1/6.
So we're done with part (a).
We haven't seen any
conditioning yet.
The conditioning comes
in part (b).
So in part (b) we're still
interested in the event D, in
the event that "doubles are
rolled." But now we want to
compute this probability
conditioned on the event that
the sum of the results is
less than or equal to 4.
So I'm going to use this
shorthand "sum less than or
equal to 4" to denote the event
that the role results in
the sum of 4 or smaller.
So there's two ways we're
going to go about
solving part (b).
Let's just jump right
into the first way.
The first way is applying the
definition of conditional
probability.
So hopefully you remember that
this is just probability of D
intersect "sum less than or
equal to 4", divided by
probability of "sum less
than or equal to 4".
Now, "sum less than or equal
to 4" and D intersect "sum
less than or equal to 4"
are just two events.
And so we can apply the discrete
uniform law to
calculate both the numerator
and the denominator.
So let's start with the
denominator first because it
seems a little bit easier.
So "sum less than or equal to
4", let's figure this out.
Well, 1-1 gives us a sum
of 2, that's less
than or equal to 4.
2-1 gives us 3.
3-1 gives us 4.
4-1 gives us 5, so we don't want
to include this or this,
or this point.
And you can sort of convince
yourself that the next point
we want to include
is this one.
That corresponds to 2-2, which
is 4, so it makes sense that
these guys should form the
boundary, because all dots
sort of up and to the right
will have a bigger sum.
3-1 gives us 4.
And 1-2 gives us 3.
So these six points--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6--
are the outcomes that comprise
the event "sum less than or
equal to 4".
So we can go ahead and write in
the denominator, 6 over 36,
because we just counted the
outcomes in "sum less than or
equal to 4" and divided
it by the number
of outcomes in omega.
Now, let's compute
the numerator.
D intersect "sum less
than or equal to 4".
So we already found the
blue check marks.
Those correspond to "sum less
than or equal to 4".
Out of the points that have blue
check marks, which ones
correspond to doubles?
Well, they're actually
already circled.
It's just these two points.
So we don't even need to circle
those, so we get 2 over
36, using the discrete
uniform law.
And you see that these two
36s cancel each other.
So you just get 2/6 or 1/3.
So that is one way of solving
part (b), but I want to take
you, guys, through a different
way, which I think is
important, and that make sure
you really understand what
conditioning means.
So another way that you can
solve part (b) is to say, OK,
we are now in the universe,
we are in the conditional
universe, where we know
the sum of our
results is 4 or smaller.
And so that means our new sample
space is really just
this set of six points.
And one thing that it's worth
noting is that conditioning
never changes the relative
frequencies or relative
likelihoods of the different
outcomes.
So because all outcomes were
equally likely in our original
sample space omega, in the
conditional world, the
outcomes are also
equally likely.
So using that argument, we could
say that in our sort of
blue conditional universe
all of the
outcomes are equally likely.
And therefore, we can apply a
conditional version of the
discrete uniform law.
So namely, to compute the
probability of some event in
that conditional world.
So the conditional probability
that "doubles are rolled", we
need only count the number of
outcomes in that event and
divide it by the total
number of outcomes.
So in the conditional world,
there's only two outcomes that
comprise the event "doubles
rolled." These are the only
two circles in the
blue region.
So applying the conditional
version of our
law, we have two.
And then we need to divide
by the size of omega.
So our conditional universe,
we've already said, has six
possible dots.
So we just divide by 6, and you
see that we get the same
answer of 1/3.
And so again, we used two
different strategies.
I happen to prefer the second
one, because it's slightly
faster and it makes you think
about what does conditioning
really mean.
Conditioning means you're now
restricting your attention to
a conditional universe.
And given that you're in this
conditional universe where the
sum was less than or equal
to 4, what is then the
probability that doubles
also happened?
OK, hopefully you, guys,
are following.
Let's move on to part (c).
So part (c) asks for the
probability that at least one
die roll is a 6.
So I'm going to use the letter
S to denote this, the [event]
that at least one
die roll is a 6.
So let's go back to
our picture and
we'll use a green marker.
So hopefully you agree that
anything in this column
corresponds to at least one 6.
So this point, this point, this
point, this point, this
point, and this point your first
die landed on a 6, so at
least one 6 is satisfied.
Similarly, if your second die
has a 6, then we're also OK.
So I claim we want to look
at these 11 points.
Let me just check that,
yeah, 6 plus 5--
11.
So using the discrete uniform
law again, we get
11 divided by 36.
OK, last problem, we're
almost done.
So again, we're interested in
the event S again, so the
event that at least one
die roll is a 6.
But now we want to compute the
probability of that event in
the conditional world where
the two dice land
on different numbers.
So I'm going to call this
probability of S. Let's see,
I'm running out of letters.
Let's for lack of a better
letter, my name is Katie, so
we'll just use a K. We want to
compute the probability of S
given K. And instead of using
the definition of conditional
probability, like we did back in
part b, we're going to use
the faster route.
So essentially, we're going to
find the number of outcomes in
the conditional world.
And then we're also going to
compute the number of outcomes
that comprise S in the
conditional world.
So let's take a look at this.
We are conditioning on the event
that the two dice land
on different numbers.
So hopefully you agree with me
that every single dot that is
not on the diagonal, so every
single dot that doesn't
correspond to doubles, is a
dot that we care about.
So our conditional universe of
that the two dice land on
"different numbers", that
corresponds to these dots.
And it corresponds
to these dots.
I don't want to get this one.
OK, that's good.
So let's see, how many outcomes
do we have in our
conditional world?
And I'm sorry I don't know why
I didn't include this.
This is absolutely included.
I'm just testing to see if you,
guys, are paying attention.
So we counted before that there
are six dots on the
diagonal, and we know that
there are 36 dots total.
So the number of dots, or
outcomes to use the proper
word, in our conditional world
is 36 minus 6, or 30.
So we get a 30 on
the denominator.
And now we're sort of using a
conditional version of our
discrete uniform law, again.
And the reason why we can do
this is, as I argued before,
that conditioning doesn't change
the relative frequency
of the outcomes.
So in this conditional world,
all of the outcomes are still
equally likely, hence we can
apply this law again.
So now we need to count the
number of outcomes that are in
the orange conditional world,
but that also satisfy at least
one die roll is a 6.
So you can see--
1-- we just need to count the
green circles that are also in
the orange.
So that's 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
So we get a 10, so our answer
is 10 over 30, or 1/3.
So now we're done with
this problem.
As you see, hopefully, it
wasn't too painful.
And what are the important
takeaways
here for this problem?
Well, one is that whenever you
have a discrete sample space,
in which all of outcomes are
equally likely, you should
think about using the discrete
uniform law, because this law
lets you reduce the problem from
computing probabilities
to just counting outcomes
within events.
And the second takeaway is
the way we thought about
conditioning.
So we talked about one thing,
which is that in your
conditional world, when you
condition, the relative
likelihoods of the various
outcomes don't change.
So in our original universe,
all of the outcomes were
equally likely.
So in our conditional universe,
all of the outcomes
are equally likely.
And we saw it was much faster to
apply a conditional version
of the discrete uniform law.
So that's it for today.
And we'll do more problems
next time.