Hi everyone.
Today I'm going to talk about
Bernoulli process practice
number one.
In this problem, you are
visiting a rain forest.
But unfortunately you have
run out of insect repellent.
As a result, the probability
of you getting mosquito bites
is really high.
At each second, the
probability that a mosquito
will land on your neck is 0.5.
If a mosquito
lands on your neck,
the probability that it
will bite you is 0.2.
And the probability that it
will never bother you is 0.8.
All of this happens
independently
among all mosquitoes.
For part (a) of
the problem, we're
interested in finding
the expected value
of the time between
successive mosquito bites
and the variance of the time
between successive mosquito
bites.
From the problem
statement we know
that the probability
distributions
of getting mosquito
bites at different times
are identically distributed
and independent.
Therefore, the mosquito bites
occur as a Bernoulli process
with parameter p, where p
represents the probability
of getting a mosquito
bite at each second.
And p can be calculated
as the probability
that a mosquito lands on
your neck at each second
multiplied by the probability
that a mosquito will bite you,
given that it has
landed on your neck.
And this is equal to 0.5 times
0.2, which is equal to 0.1.
Next let us define X as the
time between successive mosquito
bites.
Because of the
memoryless property
of the Bernoulli
process, which means
the probability of
getting mosquito
bites at different
times are independent,
X is equivalent to the time
until the next mosquito bite.
And X is a geometrical
random variable
whose PMF is like the following.
For all x, less
than or equal to 0,
the probabilities
are equal to 0.
For x equal to 1,
the probability
that it takes 1 second
to the next mosquito bite
is simply equal to p.
And for x equal to
2, the probability
that it takes 2 seconds
until the next mosquito
bite is equal to
1 minus p times p.
And for x equal to
3, the probability
that it takes 3 seconds until
the next mosquito bite is equal
to 1 minus p to the
power of 2, times p.
Similarly, for x equal
to k, the probability
that it takes k seconds
until the next mosquito bite
is equal to 1 minus p to the
power of k minus 1, times p.
Therefore the expected
value of X is equal to 1
over p, which is equal to 1
over 0.1, which is equal to 10.
And the variance of X is equal
to 1 minus p over p squared,
which is equal to 1 minus
0.1 over 0.1 squared, which
is equal to 90.
For part (b) of
the problem, we're
considering another type of bug.
Similar to the case as the
mosquitoes, here at each second
the probability that a
tick will land on your neck
is equal to 0.1.
And if a tick
lands on your neck,
the probability that it will
bite you is equal to 0.7.
And the probability that
it will never bother you
is equal to 0.3.
And all this happens
independently
among all ticks
and all mosquitoes.
So similar to the
case as part (a),
where mosquito bites
occur as a Bernoulli
process with parameter
p equal to 0.1,
here the tick bites also
occur as a Bernoulli process
with parameter q
equal to 0.1 times
0.7, which is equal to 0.07.
And q is the probability
of getting a tick
bite at each second.
Therefore, the bug bites
occur as a merged process
from the mosquito bites
and the tick bites.
And let r represent the
parameter for the bug bites.
So here r is equal
to the probability
of getting either a mosquito
bite or a tick bite.
And this is equivalent to
1 minus the probability
of getting no mosquito
bite and no tick bite.
Because the mosquito
bites and the tick
bites happen independently,
therefore, this
can be written as 1 minus the
probability of no mosquito
bites times the probability of
no tick bites at each second.
And this is equal to 1
minus p times 1 minus q,
which is p plus
q minus pq, which
is equal to 0.1 plus
0.7 minus 0.1 times 0.7.
Which is equal to 0.163.
Next, let us define Y as the
time between successive bug
bites.
So similar as X in
part (a), here Y
is a geometric distribution
with parameter r.
And therefore the expected
value of Y is equal to 1
over r, which is
equal to 1 over 0.163.
That is approximately 6.135.
And the variance of Y is equal
to 1 minus r over r squared,
which is equal to 1 minus
0.163 over 0.163 squared.
And this is
approximately 31.503.
So this gives us
the expected value
of the time between
successive bug bites
and the variance of the time
between successive bug bites.
And this concludes our today's
practice on Bernoulli process.