Hi.
In this problem, we're going to
look at competing exponentials.
So, we have three
exponential random variables.
X with parameter lambda,
Y with parameter mu,
and Z with parameter nu.
And we want to calculate
some probability.
And the probability that
we want to calculate
is the probability that X is
less than Y is less than Z.
Now, we can reinterpret this
as three Poisson processes,
because the link
between exponentials
and Poisson processes is
that the interarrival time
of Poisson processes are
exponentially distributed.
So, you can think of X being
the time until the first arrival
in a Poisson process
with parameter lambda.
And same thing for Y is
the first arrival time
of a Poisson process
with parameter mu.
The same thing for Z and nu.
So, in that interpretation,
X less than Y lesson Z,
you could interpret as a race,
meaning that X finishes first,
followed by a Y, and
then Z comes in last.
So, with that
interpretation, let's see
how we can calculate
what this probability is.
We can rewrite this
probability as a combination
of two things occurring.
One is that X is less than
the minimum of Y and Z,
and then the other is
that Y is less than Z.
So, what does this
first event mean?
This first event means
that X comes in first.
And it doesn't matter
whether Y comes
in second or Z comes in second.
So, we first say that X
has to come in first, which
means it has to beat
the better [of] Y and Z.
And then that combined with
the fact that Y does better
than Z is the same thing
as saying that X is first,
Y is second, and Z is third.
And now let's try to argue
using Poisson processes
that these two events
are actually independent.
So, this event occurring means
that X is smaller than Y and Z.
So, let's take these
Poisson processes
and, because these
random variables
are assumed to be
independent, these
are independent Poisson
process, so, we can merge them.
So let's merge
these two and we'll
get a Poisson process
that has rate mu plus nu.
And we can also merge this
first one and that one,
and we'll get another
Poisson process
with parameter lambda
plus mu plus nu.
So, in that context,
what does it
mean that X is less than
the minimum of Y and Z?
It just means that, in
this merged process,
the first arrival came
from the X process.
In that case, if
that's true, then X
is less than the
minimum of Y and Z.
Well, let's say
that that event does
occur, that the first arrival
is from the X process.
Now we're interested in what
the order of the second two
arrivals are.
Is it Y first and then
Z, or Z first and then Y?
Well, it doesn't matter because
of the fresh start property.
Because, after this
arrival comes-- and say
it is from the X process-- the
Poisson processes start anew,
and they're still independent.
And so what happens
after that is
independent of what happened
here when X arrived.
Whether Y came first followed by
Z or Z came first followed by Y
is independent of
what happened here.
So, because of that, these
two events are independent.
When we have the probability
of the intersection of two
independent events,
we can write that
as the product of those
two probabilities.
Now, what is the probability
of this first event,
the probability that X is
less than the minimum Y and Z?
Well, we just said
that that corresponds
to the first arrival
of this merged process
being from the X process.
Well, that probability is lambda
over lambda plus mu plus nu.
So, it's equal to
this ratio where
the process that you're
interested in, its rate
comes in the numerator,
and then the merged rate
is on the denominator.
And what about the second one?
What's the probably
that Y is less than Z?
Well, let's go now to
this merged process
where we merge just
the Y and Z processes
and see which one comes first.
Well, in that case,
what we want to know
is, in this merged process,
what is the probability
that the first arrival
came from the Y process.
Well, analogously,
that probability
is going to be mu
over mu plus nu,
and that gives us our answer.
And so we see that what
looked like a pretty complex
calculation, when
we reinterpret it
in terms of Poisson
processes, it
becomes relatively
easy to solve.
But this still seems like
a complicated expression,
so let's try to check to
see whether it actually
makes sense.
One way to do that is to
look at a specific example
of the choice of
lambda, mu, and nu,
and see if it
actually makes sense.
One example is, suppose that
all three of these parameters
are the same.
Well, if they're all the
same, then this probability,
the first part becomes 1/3,
and the second one is 1/2.
And so, if all three
parameters are the same,
the probability becomes 1/6.
And let's see if
that makes sense.
If all three parameters
are the same,
that means that these arrival
rates are all the same.
And what that means is that
any ordering of these three
arrivals is as likely
as any other ordering.
And what we're interested
in is the probability
of one particular ordering
happening, which is X first,
then Y, then Z. But, if
everything is symmetric,
then any of the orderings is
as likely as any other one.
And how many
orderings are there?
Well, there's three choices for
who comes in first, two for who
comes in second, and one
for who comes in last.
So, there's a total
of six possible orders
in which these three
contestants, if you think
of it that way, can
finish this race.
And out of those, we
want the probability
that one of those
outcomes happens.
And so, the probability
should be 1/6,
and that's what our
formula tells us.
So, as I said, in
this problem, we
saw how to reinterpret
exponentials
in the context of
Poisson processes
that helped us solve
a probability that
looked like it was
pretty complicated.
So, I hope that was helpful,
and see you next time.