In this segment, we will discuss
the multinomial, and
the multinomial probabilities,
which are a nice
generalization of the binomial
probabilities.
The setting is as follows.
We're dealing with balls.
And the balls come into
different colors.
There are r possible
We pick a ball at random.
And when we do that, there's a
certain probability p-i that
the ball that we picked,
has the i-th color.
Now, we repeat this process,
n times independently, each
time, we get a ball that
has a random color.
And we're interested in the
following kind of question.
Somebody fixes for us
certain numbers--
n1, n2, up to nr that add up to
n, and asks us, what is the
probability that when you carry
out the experiment, you
get exactly n1 balls of the
first color, exactly n2 balls
of the second color,
and so on.
So the numbers n1, n2, and up to
nr are fixed given numbers.
For a particular choice of
those numbers, we want to
calculate this probability.
Now of course, this is
a more general model.
It doesn't necessarily
deal with balls
of different colors.
For example, we might have an
experiment that gives us
random numbers where the numbers
range from 1 up to r.
And, at each time, we get
a random number, with
probability p-i.
We get a number which
is equal to i.
So we could use this to model
die rolls, for example.
And there's actually a special
case of this problem, which
should be familiar.
Suppose that we have
only two colors.
And instead of thinking of
colors, let's think of the two
possibilities as being
heads or tails.
And we can make the
following analogy.
Somebody gives us numbers, n1
and n2 that add up to n.
And we're interested in the
probability that we get n1 of
the first color and n2
of the second color.
Well, we could think of this
as a setting in which we're
asking for the probability that
we obtain k heads and n
minus k tails.
So the question of what is the
probability that we obtain k
heads and n minus k tails is
of the same kind as what is
the probability that we get n1
of the first color and n2 of
the second color.
Now, if heads have the
probability p of occurring,
and tails has a probability of
1 minus p of occurring, then
we would have the following
analogy: the probability of
obtaining the first color, which
correspond to heads,
that would be equal to p.
The probability of obtaining
the second color, which
corresponds to tails.
This would be 1 minus p.
Now, the probability of
obtaining k heads in those n
independent trials we
know what it is.
By the binomial probabilities,
it is n choose k times p to
the k times 1 minus p to
the power n minus k.
Now we can translate this answer
to the multinomial
case, where we're dealing with
colors, and we do these
substitutions.
So n choose k is n factorial
divided by k factorial.
In this case, k is
the same as n1.
So we get an n1 factorial.
And then we're going to have
here n minus k factorial.
But n minus k corresponds
to n2.
So here we get an
n2 factorial.
And then p corresponds to p1.
And p2 corresponds
to 1 minus p.
So we get here p1 times p2.
And the power n minus k, again,
by analogy, is n2.
So this is the form of the
multinomial probabilities for
the special case where we're
dealing with two colors.
Let's now look at the
general case.
Let's start with an example.
To be concrete, suppose that the
number of colors is equal
to 3 and that we're going to
pick n equal to 7 balls.
We carry out the experiment.
And we might obtain an outcome
which would be a
sequence of this type.
So the first ball had
the color one.
The second ball had
the first color.
The third ball had
the third color.
The fourth had the first
color, and so on.
And suppose that this
was the outcome.
One way of summarizing what
happened in this outcome would
be to say that we
had four ones.
We had two twos, and
we had one three.
We would say that this is
the type of the outcome.
It's of type 4, 2, 1.
That is, we obtain 4 of the
first color, 2 of the second
color, and 1 of the
third color.
This is one possible outcome.
What is the probability
of obtaining
this particular outcome?
The probability of obtaining
this particular outcome is,
using independence, the
probability that we obtain
color 1 in the first trial.
color 1 in the second trial,
color 3 in the third trial,
color 1 in the fourth trial,
color 2 in the next trial,
color 2 in the next trial, color
1 in the last trial.
And we put all of the
factors together.
And we notice that this is p1
to the fourth, p2 to the
second, times p3.
It's not a coincidence that the
exponents that we have up
here are exactly the counts that
we had when we specified
the type of this particular
outcome.
Generalizing from this example,
we realize that the
probability of obtaining a
particular sequence of a
certain type, that probability
is of this form.
For each color, we have the
probability of that color
raised to the power of how many
times that particular
color appears in a sequence.
So any particular sequence
of this type has this
probability.
What we're interested in is to
find the total probability of
obtaining some sequence
of this type.
How can we find this
probability?
Well, we will take the
probability of each sequence
of this type, which is this
much, and it's the same for
any particular sequence, and
multiply with the number of
sequences of this type.
So how many sequences are
there of a certain type?
Let's look back at
our example.
We had seven trials.
So let us number here the
different trials.
And when I tell you that a
particular sequence was
obtained, that's the same as
telling you that, in this set
of trials, we had
the first color.
In this set of trials, the fifth
and the sixth trial, we
had the second color.
And in this trial, the third
trial, we had the third color.
This is an alternative
way of telling you
what sequence we obtained.
I tell you at which trials we
had the first color, at which
trials we had the second, at
which trials we had the third.
But what do we have here?
Here we have a partition of the
set of numbers from 1 up
to 7 into three subsets.
And the cardinalities of those
subsets are the numbers that
appear here in the type
of the sequence.
The conclusion is that a
sequence of a certain type is
equivalent, or can be
alternatively specified, by
giving you a partition of the
set of tosses, which is the
set from 1 up to n, how many
trials we had, a partition
into subsets of certain sizes.
So this allows us now to count
the number of sequences of a
certain type.
It's exactly the same as the
number of partitions.
And we know what this is.
And putting everything together,
the probability of
obtaining a sequence of a
certain type is equal to the
count of how many sequences do
we have of a certain type,
which is the same as the number
of partitions of a
certain type, times the
probability of any particular
sequence of that type that
we're interested in.
So this is a formula that
generalizes the one that we
saw before for the case where
we have only two colors and
which corresponded to the
coin tossing setting.
And it is a useful model because
you can think of many
situations in which you have
repeated trials, and, at each
trial, you obtain one
out of a finite
set of possible results.
There are r different
possible results.
You repeat those trials
independently.
And you may be interested in
the question of how many
results of the first kind, of
the second kind, and so on,
there will be.