Hi.
In this problem, we're
going to get more practice
working with Poisson processes.
And in particular,
we're going to look
at how to merge two
Poisson processes,
and then think about where each
arrival in the merged process
came from.
In this problem, we
have a service station
that services jobs of two types.
Type A jobs we're told arrive
as a Poisson process with a rate
lambda A equals 3
jobs per minute.
Type B jobs also arrive as a
Poisson process with a rate
lambda B equals 4
jobs per minute.
And we're also told
that these two Poisson
processes are independent.
Part (a) is looking for the
PMF, expectation, and variance
of the number of
total jobs that arrive
in any 3-minute interval.
Let's define a random
variable for that.
So let's let N be the number
of total jobs in 3 minutes.
We know that for
[a] Poisson process,
the distribution for the number
of arrivals in any given time
interval tau is given by
a Poisson distribution.
But we have to do a little
bit more in this case
because we're looking for
the number of total jobs.
And here, we're only
given Poisson processes
for the individual
types of jobs.
But because they're independent,
what we can do first
is merge these two processes.
And what we'll get is a merged
process with a rate lambda
that's equal to the sum of
the two individual lambda
A and lambda B. So what we get
is total jobs arrive at a rate
lambda equals to 7 jobs per
minute in this merged process.
Now, what we can do is apply
the Poisson distribution
to this merged process.
So in general, the
Poisson distribution
is equal to lambda
times tau to the n times
e to the minus lambda
tau over n factorial.
In our case, lambda
we just said was 7.
We're given that
we're interested
in a 3-minute
interval, so tau was 3.
So let's substitute that in and
we get lambda times tau is 21.
So we get 21 to the n times e to
the minus 21 over n factorial.
And we should
specify that this is
valid for n equals
0, 1, 2, and so on.
The last part of
this part (a) asks us
for the expectation
and the variance.
We know that the expectation
of a Poisson random variable
is equal to lambda tau.
In this case, lambda tau is 21.
We also know that the variance
of a Poisson distribution
is, again, equal to lambda tau.
So the variance of n is
also equal to 21 here.
OK, in part (b), we're told that
we have a 10-minute interval
and we know that there were
exactly 10 total jobs that
arrived in this
10-minute interval.
And what we're asked to
find is the probability
that exactly 3 of these
10 jobs were of type A.
So in order to do that, let's
go back to our merged process
and consider any arrival
in this merged process.
Let's say this one.
We know that the
probability that any arrival
in the merged process
came from type A
given that there
was an arrival, we
know that this probability is
equal to this ratio, lambda
A over lambda A plus lambda
B. And so in this case,
we know that given
that there was
an arrival in this
merged process,
so there was some job of
either type that arrived,
the probability that that
job was of type A is 3/7.
And the other thing
that we can note
is that suppose
that we consider now
another arrival in
this merged process.
We also know that whether
or not this arrival
was of type A is independent of
whether or not this arrival is
of type A. Because of the fresh
start property of the Poisson
process.
So after this arrival arrives,
the process starts anew.
And so what happens here
is independent of what
happens here.
Now, part (b),
remember, is asking us
for the probability
of exactly 3 type
A jobs out of 10 total jobs.
Now, we can think of this
from the lens of successes
out of total number of trials.
If we view an arrival coming
from type A as a success,
then what we're looking
for is the probability
of 3 successes out of
a total of 10 trials.
And that sounds like a binomial.
And so that is exactly
what we're going to do.
We want to find the probability
of 3 successes in 10 trials.
And we've just calculated that
the probability of any given
trial being a success is 3/7.
And so by using the binomial,
we know that this is equal to 10
choose 3 times 3/7 to
the third power times 4/7
to the seventh power.
Now, part (c) is telling
us that we started
at-- suppose we
start at some time 0
and we focus only on what
happens after this time.
We want to know, what is
the distribution, the PMF,
of the number of type B arrivals
until the first type A arrival?
Everything is relative to
after some arbitrary time 0.
So let's say-- this is
again, our merged process.
These are the arrivals in the
merged process and each one
can be of either
type A or type B.
For example, say this is
where the first type A arrival
occurs.
Well, what that
immediately tells
us is that these three prior
arrivals were all of type B.
And so what we can
take away from this
is that once we know when the
first type A arrival occurs,
that tells us immediately how
many Type B arrivals there
were up to that
first type A arrival.
And this is exactly
the quantity that we're
trying to find the PMF of.
OK.
And if you think about it,
what we're looking for now
is related to the
number of arrivals
until the first type A arrival.
And that sounds
like a geometric.
The number of trials until the
first success, where success
now we can think of
as a type A arrival.
OK, so let's define a
random variable again,
K. K is the number of B arrivals
until the first A arrival.
That's what we want to find.
And the PMF of K, this
is the probability
that there are k
arrivals, k B arrivals up
to the first A arrival.
And what we've just
said is that that
is equivalent to being-- that
the first A arrival occurs
on the k plus 1-- occurs
on arrival number k plus 1.
So if this is arrival
number k plus 1,
then we know that
there were exactly
k B arrivals prior to it.
OK, so what is the probability
that first A arrival is
at k plus 1?
Well, that means that it's going
to be the geometric because we
need k failures followed by a
success at the k plus 1 trial.
So we need k failures.
Meaning that the first
k arrivals must all
have come from type B. And we
can do a similar argument here
to show that for any
arrival, the probability
that it's from type B is
just lambda B over lambda A
plus lambda B, is 4/7.
So we need the first k of those
to be of type B. And then, we
need the k plus 1
arrival to be of type A.
And that's with probably 3/7.
And so that gives us our answer.
And this is valid for k
equals 0, 1, 2, and so on.
OK.
And so in this problem,
we got some more practice
with Poisson
processes, specifically
thinking about how
to merge processes.
And then, taking
the merged process
and calculating
probabilities related
to going back to the
source, the origin,
whether it was from lambda A
or lambda-- type A or type B.
And we saw that there
are some connections
that we can make to the binomial
and the geometric in this case.
So I hope that was helpful
and see you next time.