Hi.
In this problem, we're going
to look at random incidence
under Erlang arrivals.
First, let's parse
what that means.
In a Poisson process, remember,
the time between arrivals,
or the inter-arrival
time, is distributed
as an exponential
random variable.
And random incidence
for a Poisson process
refers to the somewhat
surprising result
that when you consider
a specific time,
say, t-star, then the length
of the inter-arrival interval
that contains that time
t-star is not distributed
as an exponential
random variable.
It's actually distributed as an
Erlang random variable of order
2 or it's distributed
as a sum of two
exponential random variables.
And the reason for that is
that it comprises of two parts.
One is the time since
the last arrival
until t-star, which is
exponentially distributed,
and the time from t-star
until the next arrival, which
is also exponentially
distributed.
So that brings us
to a review of what
Erlang random variables are.
An Erlang random
variable of order k
is just the sum of k
independent and identically
distributed exponential
random variables.
So to be more specific, if Ti is
an exponential random variable
with parameter lambda, then
if you take k iid copies of Ti
and add them up,
and call that Yk,
then Yk is an Erlang
random variable of order k.
And one other fact is
that the mean of Yk,
the mean of an Erlang
random variable of order k,
is just k, the
order, over lambda,
which is the rate of the
underlying exponential random
variables.
So as a consequence, if you
have an Erlang random variable
of order two and that random
variable also has a mean of two
over lambda, we can interpret
that random variable as just
being the sum of two
exponential random variables.
2 iid exponential random
variables, T1 and T2,
where each one is exponential
with the rate lambda.
OK, so in this problem now,
we're dealing with random
incidence not under
Poisson processes,
but under something else, which
we call here an Erlang process
with Erlang arrival times.
So to be more specific,
what we're saying is that,
instead of an inter-arrival
time being exponentially
distributed, in this process, an
inter-arrival time is actually
distributed as an Erlang random
variable of order 2 with mean 2
over lambda.
So to be explicit, this is
no longer a Poisson process.
It's some other process because
the inter-arrival times are not
exponential.
So let's make use of this fact
that we talked about earlier
because now we know that the
inter-arrival times of this
Erlang process are Erlang order
2 with mean 2 over lambda.
But we know that that can just
be re-interpreted as a sum
of two simple exponentials,
each with parameter lambda.
So let's just draw another
picture and imagine that
for each of these arrivals,
so say we have three sample
arrivals in this Erlang
process, we can fill in, kind
of, the gaps between these
with additional arrivals.
And then think of each one
of these times as all being
exponential with
parameter lambda.
So this is a valid
interpretation because when we
connect these, these
inter-arrival times correspond
to the combination of
two inter-arrival times,
which we know we can split that
into just two exponentials.
So each one of these is an
exponential random variable.
And when you combine them,
you get an Erlang order of 2.
But the nice thing about this
is that if we look at this
diagram, it actually is just
exactly a Poisson process with
a rate lambda because now,
what we're dealing with are
exactly-- the inter-arrival
times are now exactly
exponential random variables.
And so this is in fact, now,
just a simple Poisson process.
And we can also just think of it
as we take the Poisson process,
and take every
other arrival, say,
all the even-numbered arrivals,
and make those correspond
to the arrivals in
the Erlang process.
OK, so now let's think about
some specific time t-star.
We want to know what is the
distribution of the length
of this specific inter-arrival
interval that t-star is in.
Well, what we can do is take
it down to the level of this
Poisson process and
look at it from there.
Well, we do that because,
for a Poisson process,
we know about random incidence
for Poisson processes.
And we know how to deal
with Poisson processes.
So let's think about this now.
Well, t-star is here.
And what we know from random
incidence for a Poisson process
is that the length of this
inter-arrival interval
for the Poisson process, we
know that this is an exponential
plus an exponential.
So combined, this
is Erlang order 2.
But that only covers
from here to here.
And what we want is
actually from here to there.
Well now, we tack on an extra
exponential because we know
that the inter-arrival times--
the time between this arrival
and that arrival in the
Poisson process is just another
exponential.
And now all of these are
in disjoint time intervals.
And they're all independent.
And so the time of this
inter-arrival interval
in the Erlang process is just
going to be the sum of three
independent exponentials within
the underlying Poisson process.
And so the answer
here is actually,
it's going to be an
Erlang of order 3.
Now this is one possible
scenario for how this might
occur.
Another scenario is actually
that t-star is somewhere else.
So let's draw this again.
And suppose now, in this case,
t-star landed between an even
numbered arrival in the Poisson
process and an odd numbered
arrival.
Now it could also arrive between
an odd numbered and an even
numbered arrival.
So it could be that
t-star is actually here.
Well, but in this case, it's
actually more or less the same
thing because now what we want
is the length of this entire
inter-arrival interval,
which, in the Poisson world,
we can break it down into random
incidence within this interval,
this inter-arrival interval,
which is two exponentials,
or an Erlang of 2,
plus this interval,
which is just a standard
inter-arrival time,
which is another exponential.
So in this case as well, we have
the sum of three independent
exponential random variables.
And so, in either case, we have
that the inter-arrival time
in the Erlang process
is an Erlang of order 3.
And so the final
answer is, in fact,
that the inter-arrival time for
random incidence under these
Erlang-type arrivals is
an Erlang of order 3.
OK, so in this problem we looked
at the random incidence under
a different type of an
arrival process, not Poisson,
but with Erlang
random variables.
But we used the insight
that Erlang really can be
re-interpreted as the sum of
independent and identically
distributed exponential
random variables.
And exponential random variables
can be viewed as one way
of interpreting and
viewing a Poisson process.
And so by going
through those steps,
we were able to use what we know
about random incidence under
Poisson processes to help us
solve this problem of random
incidence under Erlang arrivals.
So I hope that was helpful.
And I'll see you next time.