- The fire department
receives emergency calls
from all over the city.
If we believe that calls
occur in a completely
random and
uncoordinated fashion,
how do we translate these
beliefs into a tractable model?
Then, once we have
a model, there
are many questions
we may want to raise.
For example, how many calls are
expected tomorrow afternoon?
How much does this
number fluctuate?
What is the
probability that there
are no calls within
the next three hours?
The fire department
also distinguishes
between different
types of calls,
for example, those
related to fires
or the less serious
calls, like whenever
a cat is stuck on a tree.
How do we refine our model to
account for the different types
of calls?
What can we say about the
number of less serious calls
before the first
call about the fire?
In this unit, we will
study Bernoulli processes
in discrete time and
Poisson processes
in continuous time, which
provide the framework
for describing and analyzing all
sorts of situations involving
a sequence of requests
or customer arrivals.