In this problem, we're going
to look at how to use the
Central Limit Theorem to
estimate the probability of
making the wrong decision.
And the decision that we're
trying to make in this problem
is to decide whether or not a
roulette wheel at the casino
is fair or not.
So a roulette is just the game
at the casino where there are
a bunch of numbers on a wheel.
You spin the wheel, you throw a
ball onto the wheel, and you
bet on which number the ball
is going to land on.
So in this case, we're going to
deal with a wheel with 36
numbers, 1 through 36.
And we're going to try to tell
whether or not this roulette
wheel is fair.
OK.
So the way we're going to do
that is we're going to observe
what number the ball lands
on for 100 times.
We're going to look at how many
times out of those 100,
the ball lands on
an odd number.
So there's half odd numbers,
half even numbers.
And if it's fair, we would
expect that about 50 times out
of 100, it'll land
on an odd number.
And so our decision rule is
going to be if more than 55
out of the 100 times, the ball
lands on an odd number, we're
going to say that the roulette
wheel is not fair.
OK.
And now, what we want to know
is, given that rule, what's
the probability that we'll make
a wrong mistake, meaning
that more than 55 times out of
100, the ball lands on an odd
number, but in fact,
the roulette
wheel actually is fair?
OK.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to assume that the
roulette wheel is fair, meaning
that all the 36
numbers are equally likely
to be landed on.
And we're going to test, or
we're going to try to
calculate, what the probability
of making a
mistake is.
So let's define a random
variable let's call it S,
where S is number of times you
get an odd number out of 100.
And so we assume, also, that
each of the times you play
this game, it's independent.
And so what we have is that
this is just the number of
times you have success, where we
can define success as being
you get an odd number.
And so then S is just a binomial
random variable,
where you have 100 trials, and
the probability of success on
each trial, because we assume
that the roulette wheel is
fair, is 1/2--
50/50 chance of getting an odd
versus an even number.
And so because of that, we
know from binomial random
variables that the expectation
is just n times p.
n is 100. p is 0.5 here.
So you expect to get
50 odd numbers.
And the standard deviation
of S--
for a binomial, it's the square
root of np 1 minus p.
In this case, it's 100
times 1/2 times 1/2.
So it's the square root of 25.
So the standard deviation
is 5.
And now, if you actually
wanted to calculate the
probability that you'll
make an error--
well, how do you make an
error in this case?
We assume that the roulette
wheel is fair.
So in that case, you'll make
an error if you actually do
get more than 55 odd numbers.
And what is the probability
of that?
The probability which you're
looking for is the probability
that S is greater than 55.
If this event occurs, then you
will make a mistake, because
you will say that the roulette
wheel is not fair, when, in
fact, it is.
OK.
So how do you calculate this?
Well, you can calculate it using
the actual binomial PMF.
And what it'll amount to
is a big summation.
So it'll be the summation of--
you have to get anywhere between
56 to 100 odd numbers.
For each one of those, there
is 100 choose k orders in
which those k odd numbers can
appear out of the 100 trials.
And then you have the
probability of success is 1/2.
The probability of failure
is also 1/2.
And so because of that,
it just simplifies
to 1/2 to the 100.
So this is just the standard
binomial PMF.
And you just take
this summation.
Now, this is kind
of complicated.
So what we're going to do is
look for an approximation to
this using Central
Limit Theorem.
All right.
So there are different
ways of doing this.
And we'll actually go through
three different
ways of doing this.
The first one is--
well, the probability that we're
looking for is this.
And so we do the standard
converting
to a standard normal.
So what we do is we
subtract the mean.
We subtract the mean and
divide by the standard
deviation on both sides.
And then we invoke the Central
Limit Theorem.
And we say that this is
approximately the probability
that Z, the standard normal,
is greater than--
well, 5 over 5 is 1, which
is just 1 minus Phi of 1.
And if you go in the standard
normal tables, you can find
out what Phi of 1 is.
It turns out it's 0.8413.
And so the approximation that
you get here is 0.1587.
So this is your approximate
probability of being wrong--
saying that the roulette
wheel is unfair
when, in fact, it is.
OK.
So notice that we've actually
used 55 here
with this strict equality.
Because S is a binomial, this is
fine, because it turns out
that this probability that S is
strictly greater than 55 is
exactly the same as the
probability that S is greater
than or equal to 56.
Because S a binomial,
it's discrete.
It takes only integer values.
It can't be anything
between 55 and 56.
So these are actually
the same.
So we can take that and now use
56 in our Central Limit
Theorem approximation.
So what that tells us is now,
we can rewrite it as this--
56 minus the mean over the
standard deviation.
Now, because when we take this
conversion and invoke the
Central Limit Theorem, what
we'll get is that this is
approximately the probability
that Z is greater than or
equal to 6 over 5, or 1.2.
And this is again, of course,
1 minus Phi of 1.2.
And then if you look at the
tables again, this is
approximately 0.1151.
So with 55, we got 0.1587.
With 56, we got 0.1151.
They're not too different.
But there is a fairly
significant percentage change
between the two.
So which one is right?
Or is there an even
better way, some
kind of middle ground?
And that is exactly the
third way of doing it.
And this is also the de
Moivre-Laplace approximation
to the binomial.
So instead of taking just
strictly either of the two
integer values, 55 or 56, what
we do is we take the middle
ground, and we say that, well,
let's instead approximate this
with the probability that Z is
greater than 55.5 minus the
mean over the standard
deviation.
So that would give us--
this is 1 minus, now,
Phi of 1.1.
5.5 over 5 is 1.1.
And if you look at the tables,
this will give you 0.1357.
So we have three candidate
answers.
This is the biggest.
This is the smallest.
And this is in between.
So it turns out that if you
actually calculate out this
summation, the exact answer--
or the exact answer at least
to four decimal places--
is 0.1356.
This is without any
approximations.
You actually calculate the exact
probability using the
binomial distribution.
And you can see that the midway
point approximation,
the de Moivre-Laplace
approximation, is very close
to the exact answer.
And so this is, in general, the
case, especially when n is
large and p is roughly
equal to 1/2.
So when you have roughly
balanced binomial distribution
with enough samples, then
using this midway point
approximation will be
better than using
either of the two endpoints.
OK.
So this is just an example of
applying the Central Limit
Theorem, and specifically
applying it to the binomial
distribution.
And you can see that there's
different ways of doing it.
And in some cases, using the
midpoint approximation gives
you a better approximation.
OK.
I hope that was interesting,
and see you next time.