Here's a fun problem.
A sheet of paper is
ruled with parallel lines
that are at equal
distance from each other.
I throw a needle on
the paper randomly.
What is the probability
that the needle will
intersect one of the lines?
[CELL PHONE RINGING]
Here's another question.
A cell phone tower sends
signals carrying voice, text,
and digital data
to your cell phone.
These signals are always
corrupted by some noise.
How would you describe
or model the noise?
And how would you
evaluate the probability
that the signal is
incorrectly received?
In both of these examples,
we can model the underlying
phenomena in terms of
continuous random variables.
And in this unit, we will
develop methods to answer
the questions we raised.