By this point in this class, we
have developed all of the
basic tools that we need
to study and analyze
probabilistic models.
So this is a good time to move
to a practical subject, the
subject of inference.
The general idea is that we
have a probabilistic model
involving several random
variables.
We observe the values
of some of them.
And we want to make inferences
on some of the others.
Note that the unknown quantities
are modeled as
random variables, which
means that we can
use the Bayes rule.
And so we will stay within
the realm of
so-called Bayesian inference.
In the four lectures that
follow, we will illustrate the
use of the Bayes rule
in various settings.
We will discuss different
methods of coming up with
estimates of unobserved
random variables.
And we will illustrate
the methodology
through several examples.
If you have mastered the
material in previous units,
you should not face any
challenges here.
We will only apply tools that we
already have, together with
some new definitions
and terminology.
However, this may be a good time
to review the different
versions of the Bayes rule and
the examples covered in the
second half of lecture 10.
And by the end of this unit,
you should have a working
knowledge of the key elements
of Bayesian inference.
And you should be ready to apply
your knowledge to actual
problems, as they arise
in the real world.