In this problem, we're going
to look at the probability
that when you take a stick and
break it into three pieces
randomly, that these three
pieces can actually be used to
form a triangle.
So we start out with a stick of
unit length-- so length 1.
And we'll choose a point along
the stick to break.
And we'll choose that point
uniformly at random.
So let's say that we
chose it here.
That was a point where
we'll break it.
And then independently of this
first choice, we'll again
choose a second point to break
it, again uniformly at random,
along the entire stick.
So let's say the second point
we chose is here.
So what we have now is, we'll
break it here and here.
And so we'll have
three pieces--
the first one, the left
one, the middle one,
and the right one.
And we want to know, what's the
probability that when you
take these three pieces you
can form a triangle?
So the first thing we
should ask ourselves
is, what do you need?
What conditions must be
satisfied in order to actually
be able to form a triangle
with three pieces?
So you could think about what
would stop you from being able
to do that?
Well, one possibility is
that you have pieces
that look like this.
So in that case, you would
try to form something
that looks like this.
But you can't get a triangle,
because these two pieces are
too short, and they can't
touch each other.
So actually, the condition that
must be satisfied is that
when you take any two of the
three pieces, their combined
length has to be greater than
the length of the remaining
third piece.
And that's true for
any two pieces.
And really, that's just so that
any two pieces, they can
touch and still form
a triangle.
So let's try to add some
probability to this.
So we have a unit-length
stick.
So let's actually give
a coordinate system.
The stick goes from 0 to 1.
And let's say that we break
it at these two points.
The first point where we choose,
we'll call that X. So
that's the first point that
we choose to break it.
And then the second point we
choose, we'll call that Y.
Now, note that I've drawn it so
that X is to the left of Y.
But it could actually be the
case that the first point I
chose is here and the
second point that I
chose is to the left.
But for now, let's first assume
that's this scenario
holds, that the first
point is to the left
of the second point.
So under this assumption,
we can see that from the
definition of these random
variables, we can actually see
that the lengths are given
by these three lengths.
So the lengths are X. The
left-most piece has length X.
The second, middle, piece has
length of Y minus X. And the
last piece has length 1 minus
Y. And now, let's recall our
three conditions.
So the conditions were that any
two of these, the sum of
any two lengths has to be
greater than the length of the
third piece.
So let's do these together.
So X plus Y minus X has to be
greater than y minus 1.
So with these two pieces, you
can cover this third piece.
We also need that with the first
and third pieces, we can
cover the middle piece.
And we need with the second and
third pieces, we can cover
the first piece.
Now, this looks kind of messy,
but in fact, we can actually
simplify this.
So this actually simplifies.
X minus X-- that disappears.
And so this actually simplifies
to 2Y has
to be at least 1.
Or, even more simply, y has
to be greater than 1/2.
What about this one?
This one we can rearrange
things again.
The X we can move over here,
Y we can move over here.
And we get that 2X plus 1 has
to be greater than 2Y.
Or put in other words, Y is
less than X plus 1/2.
And for the last one, again,
we can simplify.
The Y's cancel each other out.
And we're left with
2X is less than 1.
Or X is less than 1/2.
So these are our three
conditions
that need to be satisfied.
So now, we just have to figure
out what's the probability
that this is actually
satisfied.
Now, let's go back to original
definition and see what are
the actual distributions for
these random variables, X and
Y.
Remember, we defined them to
be X is the location of the
first break and Y is the
location of the second break.
And as we said in the problem,
these are chosen uniformly at
random, and they're
independent.
And so we can actually draw
out their joint PDF.
So X and Y, it can cover any
point in the square.
And moreover, it's actually
uniform within this square,
because each one is chosen
uniformly at random.
And they're independent.
So it's anywhere in here.
And so what do we need to do?
We just need to identify what's
the probability that
these three conditions hold.
Let me adjust.
Let me write this,
line these up.
So these are our three
conditions that we need.
And now, remember, we're still
working under the assumption
that the first point that we
chose is actually to the left
of the second point.
So what does that mean?
That means that we are
actually in this top
triangle, top 1/2.
X is less than Y. So
what do we need?
We need Y to be at least 1/2.
So here's 1/2.
So we need Y to be
above this line.
We need X to be less than
1/2, so we need X to
be to the left here.
So far, we're stuck in
this upper square.
And the last thing we need is Y
to be less than X plus 1/2.
The line Y equals X plus
1/2 is this one.
So Y has to be less than that,
so we have to be in this
triangle here.
So these three conditions tell
us that in order for us to
have a triangle, we need for X
and Y to fall jointly in this
small triangle here.
And now, because the joint
distribution is uniform, we
know that the density is just
1, because the area
here is just 1.
So the height is
just 1 as well.
And so the density or the
probability of falling within
this smallest triangle is just
going to be also the area of
this triangle.
And what is the area
of this triangle?
Well, you can fit eight of
these triangles in here.
Or you could think of it as
1/2 times 1/2 times 1/2.
So the area is just 1/8.
So assuming that X is less than
Y, then the probability
forming a triangle is 1/8.
Now, that's only half the story,
because it's possible
that when you chose these two
break points, that we actually
had the opposite result, that
X, the point that you chose
first falls to the right of
the point that you chose
second, in which case everything
kind of flips.
Now, we assume that Y is less
than X, which means that now
we're in this lower triangle
in the square.
Now, we could go through this
whole exercise again.
But really, what we can see is
that all we've really done is
just swap the names.
instead.
Of having X and Y, we now
call X, we call it XY.
We call Y X.
And so if we just swap names,
we can see that--
let's just fast forward through
all these steps and
see that we could just swap
names here too as well in the
three conditions.
So instead of needing Y to be
greater than 1/2, we just need
X to be greater than 1/2.
And instead of having
X less than 1/2, we
need Y less than 1/2.
And then we also swap this.
So we need X to be less
than Y plus 1/2.
Or Y is greater than
X minus 1/2.
Now, let's figure out what
this corresponds to.
We need X to be greater
than 1/2.
So it needs to be to
the right of here.
We need Y to be less than 1/2.
So we need it to be
below this line.
And we need Y to be greater
than X minus 1/2.
What is the line Y equals
X minus 1/2?
That is this line here.
And we need Y to be
greater than that.
So it needs to be
above this line.
And so we get that this is the
triangle, the small triangle
that we need in this case.
Notice that it's exactly the
same area as this one.
And so we get another
contribution of 1/8 here.
So the final answer is,
1/8 plus 1/8 is 1/4.
So the probability of forming
a triangle using this three
pieces is exactly 1/4.
And so notice that what we've
done is, you've set things up
very methodically in the
beginning by assigning these
random variables.
You consider different cases.
Because you don't actually know
the order in which X and
Y fall, let's just assume that
one particular order and work
from there .
And then do the other
case as well.
And it just so happened that
because of the symmetry of the
problem, the second case was
actually very simple.
We could just see that it
is actually symmetric.
And so we get the same answer.
So this is kind of an
interesting problem because
it's actually a practical
application of something that
you might actually do.
And you can see that just by
applying these probability
concepts, you can actually
calculate an interesting
probability.
And the answer to this
question is 1/4.
So I hope that was interesting,
and we'll
see you next time.