Hi.
In this problem, we're
going to practice
working with Poisson processes.
And what we have is a
sequence of light bulbs
that we're going to start
using, starting at time equal 0.
And we use them
one after another.
And as soon as one
light bulb dies out,
we immediately replace
it with another one.
And we have two
types of light bulbs
to choose from-- type A
bulbs and type B bulbs.
And every time we have to
choose a new light bulb,
we pick type A or type B
with equal probability.
And also, whether we pick A or
B for any one particular light
bulb is independent
of whether we
pick A or B for any
other light bulb.
And the problem also tells us
how long each light bulb lasts.
And it's random.
And for type A, we know
from the distribution
that type A bulbs last for
an exponentially distributed
amount of time with
parameter lambda equals 1.
And type B bulbs last for
an exponentially distributed
amount of time with
parameter lambda equals 3.
And so type A bulbs
last, on average,
longer than type B bulbs.
And the last thing
that we're told
is that how long any
given type A bulb lasts
is independent of how long
any other type A bulb lasts.
And it's also
independent of how long
any other type B bulb lasts.
And the same thing
for type B bulbs.
Now, the first thing that
we're going to look at
is, what is the expected
time until the first failure?
So we start out at
time 0 with a new bulb.
And we want to
know, how long is it
going to take, on
average, before
that first light bulb dies?
So let's call that T1, the
time until the first failure.
And what we want to find is
the expected value of T1.
Well, the first thing
that we're going to notice
is that this depends on whether
the first bulb that we chose
was a type A bulb
or a type B bulb.
So let's use total expectation.
And we'll break that
up into the two cases.
So let's let A denote the event
that the first bulb was type A.
So we have the expected time
until the first failure,
given that it was a type A bulb.
We multiply that
by the probability
that it was actually
a type A bulb.
And then we do the same thing
conditioning on the fact
that it was actually
a type B bulb.
OK.
So what are all these values?
Well, if we know that
it's a type A bulb,
then the time until the
first failure is just---
the expected time until
the first failure,
it's just the expected value of
an exponential with parameter
lambda equal to 1, which
we know for an exponential,
the expected value
is 1 over lambda.
And so this conditional
expectation is one.
The probability that we choose
type A for the first bulb
is-- we know from
the problem that it's
just equal probability.
So it's 1/2.
Similarly, if it's
a type B bulb,
we know that the time is
just the expected value
of an exponential with parameter
lambda equals 3, which is 1/3.
And this probability is also
1/2 of choosing type B bulb.
And when we add
this together, we
get that this is equal to 2/3.
For part (b), we
want to find, what
is the probability
that there's no failure
before some arbitrary time t?
So let's say this is
some arbitrary time t.
What's the probability
that there's
no failure before this time?
Well, there's no failure
before this time, that's
equivalent to saying that
the first bulb that we used,
it lasted longer than t.
So in terms of the random
variable T1 that we defined,
what we want to find
is the probability
that T1 is greater
than little t.
And again, that depends on
whether it's a type A bulb
that we're using
or a type B bulb.
So let's use total probability
here and break it up
into the two possible cases.
If it's a type A bulb,
this is the probability.
And if it's a type
B bulb, we get this.
And now we need
to figure out what
these different pieces are.
If it's a type A bulb, the
probably that T1 is greater
than t is just the probability
that an exponential random
variable with parameter
1 is greater than some t.
And from the exponential random
variable, 1 minus the CDF,
we know that that is
equal to-- in general,
it's e to the minus lambda t.
And so in this
case, lambda is 1.
And so this is just
e to the minus t.
And we get 1/2 from
the probability
that it's actually
a type A bulb.
And similarly, if
it's type B, then it's
the probability that an
exponential random variable
with parameter 3
is greater than t.
And so in that case, it's e
to the minus 3t times 1/2.
And so that gives us our answer.
Let's move on to part (c).
Part (c) wants us
to know, suppose
that we do we know that there
was no failure in the first t
time, or equivalently, that the
first bulb lasted more than t.
What's the probability
that this bulb was type A?
So what's the
probability that it's
type A, given that
T1 is greater than t?
And so in effect,
we're now trying
to flip this and calculate or
try to infer whether or not
it's type A based on the
data that we collected,
which is how long the
bulb actually lasted.
And so this is now going to be
an application of Bayes' rule,
which tells us that this is
equal to the probability that
it's type A bulb times the
probability that it lasted more
than t, given that
it was a type A bulb,
over the probability that--- the
unconditional probability that
it lasted more than t.
OK.
So the probability
that it's A is 1/2.
The probability that
T1 is greater than t
given that it's A we already
calculated over here.
It's e to the minus t.
And the probability that--
the unconditional probably we
just calculated in part (b).
So we'll substitute
that in the denominator.
And the answer that
we get is this-- 1/2 e
to the minus t over 1/2
e to the minus t plus 1/2
e to the minus 3t.
OK.
Now, part (d) asks us
to find the variance
of how long the
first bulb lasts.
So what is the variance of T1?
To find the variance of T1,
let's use this expression.
The variance of T1 is
equal to the [expectation]
of T1 squared minus
the expectation
of T1 quantity squared.
We already know what
expectation of T1 is.
It's 2/3.
We calculated that in part (a).
But we still need
to figure out what
the expectation
of T1 squared is.
Now, expectation of T1
squared-- we can again
use the same sort of
idea and break it up
into the two cases-- the first
case that's is a type A bulb,
the second that
it's type B bulb.
So this is equal to
expectation of T1 squared given
that it's A times
the probability
that it's A, plus expectation
of T1 squared given that it's
B times the probability
that it's B. OK.
And we know that given
that it's a type A bulb,
this T1 is now exponential
with parameter 1.
And so we know from exponentials
that the expectation
of the square of an exponential
random variable is just---
expectation of the square of an
exponential random variable is
2 over lambda squared.
And so in this case, for
type A bulbs, lambda is 1.
So it's 2 over lambda
squared is just 2.
So this is 2 times 1/2
for the first case.
For type B bulbs, lambda is 3.
So this expectation is 2 over
3 squared, or 2/9 times 1/2.
And so we get 1
plus 1/9 is 10/9.
And so after we
substitute all that in,
we see that this variance of
T1 is equal to 10/9 minus 2/3,
from part (a),
squared, which is 4/9.
That gives us 6/9, or 2/3.
For part (e), what we're told
is that we have 12 failures.
And we want to know,
what is the probability
that the 12th failure is the
4th failure of a type A bulb?
So let's draw out a timeline
here, starting at time 0.
So here are some failures.
So suppose that
there are exactly
12 total failures
here of either type.
And we want this to be
the 4th type A failure.
Now, if that is the 4th
type A failure, what does
that mean for the previous
11 failures before that?
That means out of
the previous 11,
there were 3 A failures
out of 11 total failures.
So the probability
that we need to find
is just exactly equal
to the probability
that we have 3 A failures
out of the first 11
and that the 12th
failure was also type A.
OK.
Now, what is the probability
that out of 11, 3 of them
were of type A?
Well, that is just a binomial,
because every single time
we choose a new bulb, it's
either type A or type B.
And we said at the beginning
that each of these choices
are independent.
And so if you think of
choosing type A as a success,
this is just the probability of
3 successes out of 11 trials.
And then we also need the 12th
trial to be a success as well.
So combining that,
we get that we
have a binomial
for the first 11.
So we need 3 out of the
first 11 to be successes.
And the probability of
success is just 1/2.
And then we also need the 12th
trial to be a success as well.
And we can simplify this.
This is just 11 choose 3
times 1/2 to the 12th power.
All right.
Part (f)-- part (f)
asks a question that
looks very similar to
what part (e) asked.
Except the difference is
that now we want to know,
what is the probability that
out of the first 12 failures,
4 of them were of type A bulbs--
so 4 A out of the first 12.
So you'll notice
the difference here
is that now the
4th type A failure
is no longer fixed to
be the 12 total failure.
This 4th type A failure
could have happened earlier.
So for example, it could
have been that the first 4
bulbs were all type
A. And the last 8
were all type B. That's
possible now under part (f).
But it was not possible
under part (e).
So now this is actually a
simpler problem to solve,
because all we
care about now it's
just 4 successes out of 12.
So that probability is just 12
choose 4 times 1/2 to the 4th,
1/2 to the 8th.
And so, that simplifies to 12
choose 4 times 1/2 to the 12th.
In part (h), we want to find
the probability that two type B
bulbs combined last longer
than one type A bulb.
Type B bulbs last for an
exponentially distributed
amount of time with parameter 3.
And all times are
independent from one type B
bulb to another type B bulb.
And so when you have two
of them put together,
it's just adding two IID
exponential random variables.
And so let's define
random variable
Y to be the time of two B bulbs.
And because it's adding
two IID exponentials,
we have an Erlang
random variable.
And it has order 2 because
we're adding two exponentials.
And the parameter is the same as
the parameter of the underlying
exponential, which is 3.
And given that, we can write
what the PDF of this Erlang is.
So fY [of] y is 9y e to the
minus 3y, for y greater than 0.
And we can do the same
thing for one type A bulb.
Let's call that T. T is the time
that 1 type A bulb stays lit.
And that is just exponential
with parameter 1.
And so we know what that
distribution is as well.
It's e to the minus t for t
greater than or equal to 0.
And so what we're
asked to do now
is really just find the
probability that one of these
is greater than the other.
And we want the probability
that two B bulbs
last longer than one A bulb.
So we can write that
as the probability
that T is less than Y.
And to find what
that probability is,
we can condition.
So let's condition on
Y being some little y.
So there's that
conditional probability.
Then we multiply that by the
density of Y at that little y
and integrate.
And we should integrate
from 0 to infinity,
because that's the
range of values for Y.
OK.
So what does that equal?
Well, the first
thing we can do is
we can replace this
random variable capital
Y with some number little y,
because we are conditioning
on Y being equal to little y.
And the second thing we can
do to simplify this is we
can actually remove
this conditioning.
And the reason for
that is T and Y
are independent, because T is
related to the duration of type
A bulbs and Y is related to
the duration of type B bulbs.
And we're told in the
problem that these durations
are independent.
And so we can get rid
of this conditioning.
And now we just have this.
So to proceed, let's fill in
what these probabilities are.
What is the probability
that random variable T
is less than y?
Well, that is just a CDF of
T. And T is an exponential.
And so we know that the
CDF of an exponential
is just 1 minus e to
the minus lambda t.
In this case, it's going to
be 1 minus e to the minus y,
because lambda is 1.
And then we can also just
substitute in what the PDF of y
is from earlier.
It's 9y e to the minus 3y dy.
And so the rest of
this is just calculus.
And if we finish
the calculation,
we will get that the
probability is 7/16.
So that's one way of
doing this problem.
And so far, we
actually haven't really
seen a Poisson
process appear yet.
So let's try to come up with
another method of solving
this problem using
Poisson processes.
And there's a natural
link, because we're
talking about light
bulbs that die out
according to exponential
random variables.
And that has a
natural connection
to Poisson processes.
So let's imagine this is time 0.
And here is how long the
first light bulb lasts.
And we can consider
this an arrival.
So an arrival we can
think of as just a bulb
dying and being
replaced by new one.
And these inter-arrival
times are exponential.
And moreover, they're
independent from one
inter-arrival time to another.
And so we do have a
Poisson [process].
So let's say this is when the
next one dies out, and so on.
So how can we solve this problem
now with the Poisson process?
Let's imagine that
we were having
a race starting at time 0.
We have a race between type
A bulbs and two type B bulbs.
So they start off
at the same time.
And we want to see which
arrival comes later.
So we want a scenario
like this, for example.
If we consider a
scenario like this,
this means that the
one single type A bulb
lasted for this long, which was
longer than two type B bulbs
combined.
And so how can we come up
with the probability now?
What we can do is we can
merge these two processes.
And we can merge them because
they're both Poisson processes
and they are independent,
because the arrivals
or how long the
inter-arrival is for type
A bulbs, which is how
long type A bulbs last,
is independent of how
long type B bulbs last.
And so these processes
are independent.
We can merge them.
And so let's say we have some
arrivals in the merged process.
Now, in the type A process,
what is the arrival rate?
The arrival rate is type A
bulb's lambda, which is 1.
And for B, it's type B
bulb's lambda, which is 3.
And so in the combined,
we get a lambda of 4.
And so now how do
we actually come up
with an answer for
this probability?
Let's consider the
complement of this event.
So let's consider
T being greater
than Y, which means that the
first of the single A bulb
lasts longer than both B bulbs.
Now, how does that occur
here in the merged process?
What that corresponds
to is exactly
the case where we
have the first two
arrivals in the merged process
both are of type B bulbs.
So if that is the
case, that means
that first, a type B bulb
died and then the second B
bulbs died.
And the type A bulb
still hasn't died yet,
which means that it has
outlasted both of these.
Now, what is the probability
of this happening?
Well, we know what
the probability
of an arrival in the merged
process being from the type B
process.
That is equal to--
in general, it's
lambda B over lambda A plus
lambda B. So in this case,
it's 3/4.
Now, so what's the probability
of having a B followed by a B?
Well, these are independent.
And so the probability is just
3/4 squared, which is 9/16.
That gives you the probability
that the type A bulb
lasts longer than
the type B bulb.
And notice that it could be the
case that the very next arrival
was type A, in which case the
one type A bulb lasted longer
than both of them.
Or it could also be the case
that there were more type B
bulb arrivals until
the first type A bulb.
But it doesn't matter.
As long as the first
two were both type B,
that guarantees that the single
type A bulb lasted longer.
So that, what we just
found, is the probability
9/16 is the probability
that T is greater than Y.
So to find the probability
that Y is greater than T,
we just subtract that from 1.
And when we subtract
that from 1,
we get that it is also
the same answer-- 7/16.
So that's just another
way of calculating
the same probability.
In part (i), we're told that the
process stops after exactly 12
total bulb failures
have occurred.
And we're asked to find,
how much of that time
was illuminated by type B bulbs?
So let's define some
random variables.
Let's call V the
quantity that we actually
want to find, the total
time from type B bulbs.
So in order to
find that, we also
need to know, out of those
12 bulbs that were used,
how many were
actually of type B?
Because each time we choose
either A or B randomly.
So the number of B bulbs
out of the 12 total bulbs
is also a quantity of interest.
And finally, let's let Yi be
the time of the i-th B bulb.
So how long did the i-th B
bulb out of these 12 last?
All right.
So given that, what we know is
that V,the total time from B
bulbs out of these 12 is going
to be a sum of these individual
times from each
individual B bulb.
And it's the sum of Yi
from i equals 1 to N.
But notice that N itself
is a random variable.
So what we have is a
sum of a random number
of random variables.
And what the problem
asks us to find
is the expected value
and variance of V.
So what is the expected value?
The expected value-- we
can apply essentially,
iterated expectation.
And we know that for a
sum of a random number
of random variables,
where each one
of the individual random
variables is IID--
and that's true, because for
all B bulbs, the amount of time
that they last is exponentially
distributed with parameter 3.
So they are all IID.
So in this case, we get
that this expectation
is equal to the expectation of
N times the expectation of Yi.
So what it's essentially
saying is that,
on average, how many
B bulbs do you have?
And then multiply
that by, on average,
how long each B bulb lasts.
And that will give you
the total average time.
And so what is that?
What is the average number
of B bulbs that you get?
Well, you choose 12.
Out of 12, you want to
know how many of those
were type B bulbs.
But type A and type B bulbs
are chosen equally likely.
So on average, 6 out of these
12 will be type B bulbs.
And each one is exponential
with parameter 3.
And so the expectation of an
exponential is 1 over lambda.
And so this is 1/3.
So the answer is 2 in this case.
Now, for the variance, we
can go through the steps
and use the law
of total variance.
But for the special
case of the sum
of a random number
of random variables,
we have a simpler
formula, which is,
it's equal to the
expectation of N times
the variance of Yi plus the
expectation of Yi quantity
squared times the variance of
N. And so you see that there's
two components of this variance.
One component of
the variance comes
from randomness within
how long each bulb lasts.
And the other one comes
from randomness with respect
to how many B bulbs
there actually are.
And when you combine
both of them suitably,
then you get the total variance.
And so in this case,
expectation of N is again 6.
Variance of Yi is
the variance of
an exponential with
parameter lambda equals 3.
And that is equal to
1 over lambda squared.
And so this is 1/9.
The expectation of
exponential Yi is 1/3.
Square that and you get 1/9.
And the variance of
N is the variance
of the number of
B bulbs out of 12.
And so that N is actually
a binomial random variable,
because it's the number of
successes out of 12, where
success is a B
bulb being chosen.
And the probability of
success for each trial is 1/2.
And so for a binomial, the
variance is n times p times 1
minus p.
In this case, it's 12 times
1/2 times 1/2, which is 3.
And so what we get in the
end-- it's 6/9 plus 3/9.
And that equals 1.
In part (j), we're given
that there are no failures
until some time little t.
And conditioned on
that, we now want
to find the
conditional expectation
of the duration of the first
bulb given that information.
So let's draw a picture.
Here is time 0.
Here some t.
And what we're told is that
there are no failures from here
until here-- so no failures.
Now, what we want
to know is how long
the first bulb lasts
given that information.
So what we can see
here is that it
seems like we can apply
the memoryless property
of the exponential to help us.
So for review, suppose
that random variable X
is exponentially distributed
with some parameter lambda.
And suppose we know that X
is at least some little t.
And given that, we want to know
what the expectation of X is.
So what we know now is that, we
know that it's lasted until t.
So it's at least that big.
And from the
memoryless property,
we know that going
forward starting
from t, the additional
time after t
will also be
exponentially distributed
with the same parameter lambda.
So it's as if it's
starting over anew.
And so this
conditional expectation
is actually going to be the
expectation of X plus t.
So you know it's
lasted t already.
And then it's going to last an
additional expectation of X.
And so that's going to
be 1 over lambda plus t.
And so let's try to apply that.
But we have to be a little
bit more careful here,
because in our case, knowledge
of how long the first bulb has
lasted also gives us
some more information
about which type of bulb it was.
Because type A bulbs
last longer, on average,
than type B bulbs.
So if t is large, then that
gives us more confidence
that this bulb is
actually of type A, which
will affect how long it will
last subsequently after time t.
And so this problem (j)
will be a combination
of using the memoryless
property plus some inference
about whether it was type A
or type B. So in part (a),
we already calculated
what the expectation
of random variable T1,
where T1 is defined
to be the duration
of the first bulb.
All right.
So in part one, we
calculated the expectation
of T1 unconditioned
on anything else.
But now, we want to calculate
the conditional expectation,
the expectation of T1 given
that T1 is greater than t.
So if you remember, in part
(a), the way we did this was we
used total expectation and
split it up into two cases--
one where the first bulb
is of type A and another
where the first
bulb is of type B.
And we can do the
same thing here.
So we can split this up into
the conditional expectation
of T1 given T1 is greater than
t and the first bulb is type A.
And then we have to multiply
that by the probability
that it's actually a type A.
But another difference here
is that, remember, we're
in the conditional world
that T1 is greater than t.
So this probability also
has to be conditioned on T1
being greater than t.
And we have a similar
expression for the case
where it's a bulb of type B.
All right.
So now, let's figure out what
this conditional expectation
is, the conditional expectation
T1, given that it's at least t
and it's of type
A. So now that we
know that it's of
type A, that has
fixed what distribution T1 has.
T1 now we know is exponentially
distributed with parameter 1.
So now we can go back to
this memoryless property
and use what we found there.
So this is, in fact,
equal now to the t
that we know it's lasted already
plus an additional expectation
of an exponential
with parameter 1.
So it's t plus 1.
Or we can also get that from
here-- 1 over lambda plus t.
Now, what is the probability
that it's actually a type A,
given that it has
lasted until time t?
Well, that we've also
already calculated.
We calculated that in part (c).
And from that, from part
(c), the answer that we got
was 1/2 e to the minus t over
1/2 e to the minus t plus 1/2
e to the minus 3t.
OK.
And now, let's do
the second one.
What is the expectation of
T1, given that it's at least t
and that it's a type B bulb?
Well, now, given
that it's type B,
T1 has been fixed to be an
exponential with parameter 3.
And so this conditional
expectation is t plus 1/3.
And the probability that it's
B, given T1 is greater than t
is just 1 minus
this probability,
because it has to
be either A or B.
So 1 minus this expression
here is just 1/2 e
to the minus 3t over 1/2
e to the minus t plus 1/2
e to the minus 3t.
And we are essentially done,
because this is the answer.
We can simplify it a little
bit and write it as, t plus 1/3
plus 2/3 times 1/2 e to
the minus t over 1/2 e
to the minus t plus
1/2 e to the minus 3t.
So if we can group
this like that,
what we know is that given
that it's lasted until t,
we know that the total
time is at least t.
Plus, there's going to
be more, on average,
depending on what
type of bulb it is.
So if it's a type B
bulb, then we know,
on average, it will
last an extra 1/3.
And if it's a type
A bulb, we know
it's going to last an extra 1.
So regardless, on average, it's
going to last an extra 1/3.
And then if it's
a type A bulb, it
will last an extra 2/3 on
top of that, on average.
And so that gives
us the final answer.
So in this problem,
we've covered
a lot of different
parts in problems
related to Poisson processes.
And we started out with
looking at the perspective
of exponential random variables.
And then we tried to relate
that to a Poisson process.
And in the end, we also combined
some elements of inference
as well.
So I hope that was helpful.
And see you next time.