In the first lecture, we
introduced probabilities as a
way of describing our beliefs
about the likelihood that a
given event will occur.
But our beliefs will in
general depend on the
information that we have.
Taking into account new
information leads us to
consider so-called conditional
probabilities.
These are revised probabilities
that take into
account the new information.
Conditional probabilities are
very useful whenever we want
to break up a model into simpler
pieces using a divide
and conquer strategy.
This is done using certain tools
that we will develop and
which we will keep applying
throughout this course in
different guises.
They are also the foundation
of the field of inference.
And we will see how they
arise in that context.
Then, in the second lecture of
this unit, we will consider a
special case where one event
does not convey useful
information about another,
a situation that we call
independence.
Independence usually describes
a situation where the
occurrence or non-occurrence
of different events is
determined by factors that
are completely unrelated.
Independence is what allows us
to build complex models out of
simple ones.
This is because it is often the
case that a complex system
is made up of several components
that are affected
by unrelated, that is,
independent sources of
randomness.
And so with the tools to be
developed in this unit, we
will be ready to calculate
probabilities in fairly
complex probabilistic models.