Hi.
In this video, we're going
to do some approximate
calculations using the central
limit theorem.
We're given that Xn is the
number of gadgets produced on
day n by a factory.
And it has a normal
distribution, with mean 5 and
variance 9.
And they're all independent and
identically distributed.
We're looking for the
probability that the total
number of gadgets in 100
days is less than 440.
To start, we can first write
this as the probability of the
sum of the gadgets produced on
each of the 100 days being
less than 440.
Notice that this is the sum of
a large number of independent
random variables.
So we can use the central limit
theorem and approximate
the sum as a normal
random variable.
Then we'd basically, in order
to compute this probability,
we'd basically need to
standardize this and then use
the standard normal table.
So let's first compute
the expectation and
variance of the sum.
So I'm going to actually sum
up from 1 to n, instead of
100, to do it more generally.
So the linearity is preserved
for the expectation operator.
So this is the sum of
the expected values.
And since they're all
identically distributed, they
all have the same expectation,
and there are n of them.
And so we have this
being n times 5.
For the variance of the sum,
it's also the sum of the
variances because of
the independence.
And so they're identically
distributed to be n times the
variance of Xi.
And this is n times 9.
So now, we can standardize
it or make it 0 mean
and variance 1.
So to do that, you would
take these Xi's,
subtract their mean.
It's going to be 5 times
100 of them.
So it's 500 over the square root
of the variance, which is
9 times 100 of them.
So it's 900.
So that's less than 440 minus
500 over square root of 900.
So notice that the sum of Xi's
is a discrete quantity.
So it's a discrete
random variable.
So it may have a
PMF like this.
And we're trying to
approximate it
with a normal density.
So this is not drawn to scale.
But let's say that this is
440 and this is 439.
Basically, we're trying to say,
what's the probability of
it being less than 440?
So it's the probability that
it's 439 or 438 or 437.
But in the continuous case, a
good approximation to this
would be to take the middle,
say 439.5, and compute the
area below that.
So in this case, when we do the
normal approximation, it
works out better if we use
this half correction.
And so this, in this case,
the probability--
let's call Z the standard
normal.
And so this is approximately
equal to a standard normal,
with the probability of the
standard normal being less
than whatever that is.
If you plug that into
your calculator, you
get negative 2.02.
So now, if we try to figure out
what this, from the table,
we'll find that negative values
are not tabulated.
But we know that
the normal, the
standard normal is symmetric.
And so if we want to compute the
area in this region, it's
the same as the area in
this region above--
2.02.
So this is the same as the
probability that Z
is bigger than 2.02.
That's just 1 minus the
probability that Z is less
than or equal to 2.02.
And so that's, by definition,
Phi of 2.02.
If you look it up on the table,
2.02 has probability
here of 0.9783.
And we can just write that in.
That's the answer
for part (a).
So now, for part (b), we're
asked what's the largest n
approximately so that
it satisfies this?
So again, we can use the central
limit theorem and use
similar steps here.
So we have, in this case, for n
greater than or equal to 200
plus 5n, and standardize.
So we'll have to n.
And the mean here, this where
this comes handy,
that's going to be 5n.
And the variance is 9n.
It's greater than
or equal to--
5n's will cancel when
you subtract.
So you get 200 over the
square root of 9n.
And we can again use the half
approximation here, the half
correction here, but I'm not
going to do it to keep the
problem simple.
And so in this case, this is
approximately equal to the
probability of the standard
normal being greater than or
equal to 200 over square
root of 9n.
And so same sort
of thing here--
this is just 1 minus this.
The equal sign doesn't matter,
because Z is a continuous
random variable.
And so we have this here.
And we want this to be less
than or equal 0.05.
So that means that Phi of 200
over square root of 9 has to
be greater than or
equal to 0.95.
So we're basically looking for
something here that ensures
that this region is
at least 0.95.
So if you look at the table,
0.95 lies somewhere in between
1.64 and 1.65.
And I'm going to use 1.65 to
be conservative, because we
want this region to
be at least 0.95.
So 1.65 works better here.
And so we want this thing, this
here, which is going to
be 200 over square root
of 9n, to be bigger
than or equal to 1.65.
So n here is going to be less
than or equal to 200 over 1.65
squared 1 over 9.
So if you plug this into your
calculator, you might have a
decimal in there.
Then we just pick n,
the largest integer
that satisfies this.
So we can plug that into
your calculator.
You'll find that it's
going to be 1632.
So that's part (b).
Last part--
let n be the first day when the
total number of gadgets is
greater than 1,000.
What's the probability
that n is greater
than or equal to 220?
Again, we want to use the
central limit theorem, but the
trick here is to recognize that
this is actually equal to
the probability that the sum
from i equals 1 to 219 of Xi
is less than or equal
to 1,000.
So let's look at both directions
to check this.
If n is greater than or equal
to 220, then this has to be
true, because if it weren't
true, and if this were greater
than 1,000, then n would've
been less
than or equal to 219.
So this direction works.
The other direction, if this
were the case, it has to be
the case that n is greater than
or equal to 220, because
up until 219, it hasn't
exceeded 1,000.
And so at some point
beyond that, it's
going to exceed 1,000.
And n is going to be greater
than or equal to 220.
So this is the key trick here.
And once you see this, you
realize that this is very
easy, because we do the same
steps as we did before.
So we're looking for this.
This is equal to, again, you
do your standardization.
So this is from 219.
And you get 5 times 219 for the
mean and 9 times 219 for
the variance.
This is less than or equal to
1,000 minus 5 times 219 over
square root of 9 times 219.
Again, you can do the
half correction
here, make it 1,000.5.
But I'm not going to do that in
this case, for simplicity.
So this is approximately equal
to Z being less than
whatever this is.
And if you plug it
in, you find that
this is negative 2.14.
So in this case, we have this
is the probability that Z--
again, we do the same thing--
is greater than or
equal to 2.14.
And this is 1 minus the
probability that Z is less
than or equal to 2.14.
And that's just Phi of 2.14,
1 minus Phi of 2.14.
And that's, if you look it up
on the table, it's 2.14.
It's 0.9838.
So here's your answer.
So we're done with
part (c) as well.
So in this exercise, we did
a lot of approximate
calculations using the central
limit theorem.