Hi.
In this problem, we'll be going
over practice with the
calculation of conditional
probabilities.
We'll start with a game where
our friend Alice will be
tossing a coin with certain
bias of having a head, and
tosses this coin twice.
And we're interested in
knowing, what's the
probability that both
coin tosses will
end up being a head?
The first step we're going to
do is to convert the problem
into a mathematical form
by defining two
events as the following.
Event A is where the first
coin toss is a head.
And similarly, event B will be
having the second coin toss
also being a head.
Having these two events will
allow us to say, well, the
event that A intersection B will
be the event that both
coin tosses are a head.
And we'd like to know the
probability of such an event.
In particular, the probability
of A and B will be calculated
under two types of
information.
In the first case, we'll be
conditioning on that we know
the first coin toss is a head.
I'd like to know what the
probability of A and B is.
In the second case, we know that
at least one of the two
coin tosses is a head expressed
in the form A union
B.
And under this conditioning,
what is the probability of A
and B, A intersection B?
So Alice, in this problem,
says-- well, her guess will be
that the first quantity
is no smaller
than the second quantity.
Namely, knowing that the first
coin toss is a head somehow
more strongly implies that both
coin tosses will be a
head, compared to the case that
we only know at least one
of the two coin tosses
is a head.
And we'd like to verify if this
inequality is indeed true.
To do so, let's just use the
basic calculation of
conditional probability.
Now, from the lectures, you've
already learned that to
calculate this quantity, we'll
write out a fraction where the
numerator is the probability of
the intersection of these
two events.
So we have A intersection B
intersection A, divided by the
probability of the event that
we're conditioning on, which
is A.
Now, the top quantity, since
we know that A and B is a
subset of event A, then taking
the intersection of these two
quantities will just give
us the first event.
So we have A and B. And the
bottom is still probability of
A.
Let's do the same thing for
the second quantity here.
We have the top probability of A
and B intersection the event
A union B, and on the bottom,
probability of the event A and
B. Again, we see the event A and
B is a subset of the event
A union B. So the top will be
A and B. And the bottom--
A union B.
OK, now let's stop
for a little bit.
We've computed the probability
for each expression in the
following fractional form.
And we observed that for
both fractions, the
numerator is the same.
So the numerator is a
probability of A and B. And
the denominator in the first
case is probably of A, and the
second case, probably
of A union B.
Since we know that A is a subset
of the event A union B,
and by the monotonicity of
probabilities, we know that
the probability of A is hence
no greater than the
probability of A union B.
Substituting this back into
these expressions, we know that
because they lie in the
denominators, the first
expression is indeed no
smaller than the second
expression.
So our friend Alice
was correct.
So throughout this problem, we
never used the fact that the
probability of a particular coin
toss results, let's say,
in a head is a certain number.
Actually, this bias for the
coin is irrelevant.
Whether the coin is fair
or unfair, this
fact is always true.
So indeed, it does
not depend on the
probability of the coin.
But if you're really curious
what happens when the coin is
fair, we can plug
in the numbers.
And here, we're assuming the
coin is fair, which means
probability of having
a head is 1/2.
Then, we'll see after going
through the calculations that
the first probability is 1/2,
whereas the second probability
is 1/3, which means,
in this case, the
dominance actually is strict.
So the first one is strictly
greater than
the second one, OK?
So this completes the first
part of the problem.
How do we generalize this into
more general settings?
There are multiple ways,
but we'll go over
one particular form.
And to do so, we'll be defining
three events somewhat
more abstractly.
Let's say we have
three events--
C, D, and E. Imagine any event,
but all three events
have to satisfy the following
condition.
First, event D will be a subset
of E. And second, the
intersection of C and
D is equal to the
intersection of C and E, OK?
So this will be our
choice events.
And let's see a particular
example.
Let's say you have a sample
space here and some event E.
Now, by the first condition, D
will have to lie somewhere in
E. For the second condition,
we'll pick some event C such
that this is true.
And one way to do so is simply
picking C that lies within
both D and E. And you can see
C intersection D will be C.
And C intersection E will still
be C. Hence, the second
equality is true.
So if both equalities are true,
we have the following
relationship, that the
probability of C conditioned
on D will be no smaller than
the probability of C
conditioned on event E. And this
will be the more general
form of the inequality
that we saw before.
So first of all, the
way to prove this
is in fact the same.
We simply write out the
value of this using
the fractional form.
And based on these two facts,
we can arrive at this
equation, which I shall
now go over.
But just to see why this form
is more general, in fact, if
we, say, we let C be the event
A intersection B, D be the
event A, and E be the
event A [union]
B where A and B are the events
that we defined earlier.
We can verify that, indeed,
these conditions are true,
namely D is a subset of E.
Because A is a subset of A
union B, and C is a subset of
both D and E. And hence,
condition two is also true.
And if that's the case, we
will actually recover the
result we got earlier for events
A and B. And hence,
this equation here is
a more general form.
So that's the end
of the problem.
See you next time.