Hi.
In this video, we're going to
do standard probability
calculations for normal
random variables.
We're given that X is standard
normal with mean 0 and
variance 1.
And Y is normal with mean
one and variance 4.
And we're asked for a couple
of probabilities.
For the normal CDF, we don't
have a closed form expression.
And so people generally tabulate
values and for the
standard normal case.
So if we want little X equal to
3.49, we just look for 3.4
along the rows and 0.09 along
the columns, and then pick the
value appropriately.
So for part (a), we're asked
what's the probability that X
is less than equal to 1.5?
That's exactly phi of 1.5
and we can look that up.
1.5 directly and
that's 0.9332.
Then we asked, what's the
probability that X is less
than equal to negative 1?
Notice that negative values
are not on this table.
And the reason that is is
because the standard normal is
symmetric around zero.
And we don't really need that.
We just recognize that the area
in this region is exactly
the area in this region.
And so that's equal to the
probability that X is greater
than equal to 1.
This is equal to 1 minus
the probability that X
is less than 1.
And we can put the equal sign
in here because X is
continuous, it doesn't matter.
And so we're going to get,
this is equal to 1
minus phi of one.
And we can look up phi
of 1, which is
1.00, and that's 0.8413.
OK.
For part (b), we're asked for
the distribution of Y
minus 1 over 2.
So any linear function
of a normal random
variable is also normal.
And you can see that by using
the derived distribution for
linear functions of
random variables.
So in this case, we only need to
figure out what's the mean
and the variance of this
normal random variable.
So the mean in this case, I'm
going to write that as Y over
2 minus 1/2.
The expectation operator
is linear and so
that's going to be--
and the expectation in
this case is 1, so
that's going to be 0.
Now the variance.
For the shift, it doesn't
affect the spread.
And so the variance is exactly
going to be the same without
the minus 1/2.
And for the constant, you
can just pull that
out and square it.
And the variance of
Y we know is 4.
And so that's 1/4 times
4, that's 1.
OK.
So now we know that Y
minus 1 over 2 is
actually standard normal.
Actually for any normal random
variable, you can follow the
same procedure.
You just subtract its mean,
which is 1 in this case.
And divide by its standard
deviation and you will get a
standard normal distribution.
All right, so for part (c) we
want the probability that Y is
between negative 1 and 1.
So let's try to massage it so
that we can use the standard
normal table.
And we already know that this
is standard normal, so let's
subtract both sides
by negative 1.
And that's equal to--
I'm going to call this standard
normal Z, so that's
easier to write.
And that's equal to negative 1
less than equal to Z, less
than equal to zero.
So we're looking for this
region, 0, 1, negative 1.
So that's just the probability
that it's less than zero minus
probability that it's less
than negative 1.
Well for a standard normal, half
the mass is below zero
and a half the mass is above.
And so that's just going
to be 0.5 directly.
And for this, we've already
computed this for a standard
normal, which was
X in our case.
And that was 1 minus 0.8413.
Done.
So we basically calculated a few
standard probabilities for
normal distributions.
And we did that by looking
them up from the standard
normal table.