Hi, everyone.
Today, I'm gonna talk about
Bernoulli process, practice
number two.
In this problem, we
have a computer system
that carries out tasks
submitted by two users.
In this problem, time
is divided into slots.
At any slot, the probability
that the system is idle
is equal to 1/6.
And the probability that the
system is busy is equal to 5/6.
During any busy
slots, the probability
that the task is submitted
by user one is equal to 2/5,
and the probability that the
task is submitted by user two
is equal to 3/5.
We are assuming events
related to different slots
are all independent.
The answers to the
questions in this problem
can be found by considering
suitable Bernoulli processes.
Depending on a
specific question,
a different Bernoulli
process may be suitable.
For example, for
some of the cases,
we associate trials with slots,
and in some of the other cases,
we associate trials
with busy slots.
For part (a) of the
problem, we have
to find the probability that
a user one task is executed
for the first time
during the fourth slot.
Because the events
from different slots
are all independent,
tasks from user one
form a Bernoulli process.
The parameter of this process
represents the probability
that a task is from user
one during each slot.
That is, the parameter of p1
is equal to the probability
that a task is from user
one, during each slot.
And this is equal
to the probability
that a system is busy
during each slot, multiplied
by the probability that
the task is from user one,
given that the system is busy.
And this is equal to 5/6
times 2/5, which gives us 1/3.
And then, using the formulas
for [the] Bernoulli process,
we can calculate the
desired probability,
which is the probability
that the first user one
task occurs in slot four.
And this is equal to 1
minus p1, to the power of 3,
times p1, which is equal to 2/3,
to the power of 3 times 1/3.
For part (b) of
the problem, we're
considering the first 12 slots.
We were given that,
among the first 10 slots,
exactly five of them were idle.
And we need to find
the probability
that the sixth idle
slot is slot 12, given
that five out of the
first 10 slots were idle.
Because events that happen
during different slots
are all independent,
this probability
is equivalent to the
probability that slot 11 is busy
and slot 12 is idle.
And this is equal
to the probability
that slot 11 is busy,
multiplied by the probability
that slot 12 is idle.
Because events happening
during different slots
are independent.
And this is equal to pb times
pi, which is equal to 5/6 times
1/6, which gives us 5/36.
For part (c) of the
problem, we have
to find the expected value
of the number of slots
until the fifth
task from user one.
Let us define K as the
random variable representing
the number of slots until
the fifth task from user one.
Recall from part
(a) of the problem
that tasks from user one
form a Bernoulli process
with parameter p1, where p1
represents the probability
that a task is from user
one during each slot.
Therefore, K is a Pascal random
variable, whose distribution
looks like the following.
Probability of K equal to
t is equal to t minus 1,
choose 5 minus 1, times p1
to the power of 5, times 1
minus p1, to the
power of t minus 5,
for all t equal to
5, 6, 7, and all.
And for all t less than
5, the probabilities
are all equal to 0.
Therefore, using the formula for
the expected value of a Pascal
random variable, we can
calculate the expected value
for K, which is--
expected value of K
is equal to 5 over p1, which
is equal to 5 over 1/3,
which is equal to 15.
Therefore, the expected
value for the number
of slots until the fifth task
from user one is equal to 15.
In part (d) of the
problem, we have
to calculate the expected value
of the number of busy slots
until the fifth
task from user one.
In this part of
the problem, we're
considering a different
Bernoulli process,
with only the busy
slots, which means
we take all the busy slots
from the original process
and form this new process
with only the busy slots.
The parameter for this
new Bernoulli process
is simply p1 given B, which
represents the probability
that a task is from user
one for a busy slot.
Then, similar as
part (c), we now
define a new random
variable, N, which
represents the
number of busy slots
until the fifth
task from user one.
So here, N is a Pascal random
variable with order five
and parameter of p1
given B. Therefore,
the expected value
of N is equal to 5
over p1 given B, which
is equal to 5 over 2/5,
which is equal to 25/2.
In part (e) of
the problem, we're
interested in a
random variable that
represents the number
of tasks from user two
until the time of the
fifth task from user one.
What this means is that
out of all the busy slots
until the fifth task
from user one, T of them
were from user two and five
of them were from user one.
As defined in part
(d), that N represents
the number of busy slots until
the fifth task from user one,
we have N equal to T plus 5.
That is, out of
all the busy slots
until the fifth task
from user one, T of them
were from user two and five
of them were from user one.
And therefore, we have
T equal to N minus 5.
From part (d), we know
that the random variable
N is a Pascal random
variable with order five
and parameter p1 given
B, which is equal to 2/5.
Therefore, we can derive
the distribution for T
from the distribution
for N. So we
know that the distribution for
the Pascal random variable N
is equal to t minus 1
choose 5 minus 1, times 2/5
to the power of 5, times 1
minus 2/5 to the power of t
minus 5, for all t equal
to 5, 6, 7, and all.
And for all t less than
five, the probability for N
are all equal to 0.
Therefore, the
probability of T is simply
equal to the
probability of N at t
plus 5, which is equal to t plus
4 choose 5 minus 1, times 2/5
to the power of 5 times 1
minus 2/5 to the power of t,
for all t equal to 0, 1, 2, and
all, and for all t less than 0,
we have a probability
of T equal to 0.
Similarly, we can find
expected value of T
from the expected value of N,
which is-- expected value of T
is equal to the expected
value of N minus 5,
which is equal to 5
over 2/5, minus 5.
And this comes from
the expected value
of a Pascal random variable.
And this gives us 7.5.
And similarly, the
variance of T is
equal to the variance of the
Pascal random variable N,
which is equal to 5
times 1 minus 2/5,
over 2/5 to the power of 2.
And this concludes
our today's practice
on the Bernoulli process.