Hi.
In this problem, we have an
absent-minded professor who
will inadvertently give us some
practice with exponential
random variables.
So the professor has made two
appointments with two students
and inadvertently made them
at the same time.
And what we do is we model the
duration of these appointments
with an exponential
random variable.
So remember, an exponential
random variable is a
continuous random variable that
takes on non-negative
values, and it's parametrized
by a rate parameter, lambda.
And the exponential random
variable is often used to
model durations of time-- so
time until something happens,
so for example, in this case,
time until the student leaves
or the appointment is over.
Or sometimes you will also use
it to be as a model of time
until something fails.
And one thing that will be
useful is the CDF of this
exponential random variable.
So the probability that it's
less than or equal to some
value, little t, is equal to 1
minus e to the minus lambda t.
So this is, of course, valid
only when t is non-negative.
The other useful property is
that the expected value of an
exponential random variable
is just 1 over
the parameter lambda.
And the last thing that we'll
use specifically in this
problem is the memoryless
property of
exponential random variables.
And so recall that that just
means that if you pop in the
middle of an exponential
random variable, the
distribution for that random
variable going forward from
the point where you popped in
is exactly the same as if it
had just started over.
So that's why we call it the
memoryless property.
Basically, the past doesn't
really matter, and going
forward from whatever point
that you observe it at, it
looks as if it had just
started over afresh.
And last thing we'll use, which
is a review of a concept
from earlier, is total
expectation.
So let's actually model
this problem
with two random variables.
Let's let T1 be the time that
the first student takes in the
appointment and T2 be the time
that the second student takes.
And what we're told in the
problem is that they're both
exponential with mean
30 minutes.
So remember the mean being 30
minutes means that the lambda
is 1 over the mean.
And so the lambda in this
case would be 1/30.
And importantly, we're also
told that they are
independent.
So how long the first person
takes is independent of how
long the second person takes.
So the first student arrives on
time and take some random
amount of time, T1.
The second student arrives
exactly five minutes late.
And whatever the second person
meets with the professor, that
student will then take some
random amount of time, T2.
What we're asked to do is find
the expected time between when
the first student arrives--
so we can just call
that time 0--
and when the second
student leaves.
Now you may say, well we're
dealing with expectations, so
it's easier.
And in this case, it probably is
just the expectation of how
long the first student takes
plus the expectation of how
long the second student takes.
So it should be about 60 minutes
or exactly 60 minutes.
Now, why is that not
exactly right?
It's because there is a small
wrinkle, that the students may
not go exactly back to back.
So let's actually draw out a
time frame of what might
actually happen.
So here's time 0, when the
first student arrives.
And the first will go for some
amount of time and leave.
And now let's consider
two scenarios.
One scenario is that the first
student takes more than five
minutes to complete.
Well then the second student
will have arrived at 5 minutes
and then will be already waiting
whenever this first
student leaves.
So then the second student will
immediately pick up and continue.
And in that case, we do have two
exponentials back to back.
But there could be another
situation.
Suppose that the first student
didn't take very long at all
and finished within five
minutes, in which case the
second student hasn't
arrived yet.
So this professor is idle
in between here.
And so we actually don't
necessarily have two of them
going back to back.
So there's an empty period in
between that we have to
account for.
So with that in mind, we see
that we have two scenarios.
And so what does that
beg to use?
Well, we can split them up into
the two scenarios and
then calculate expectations
with each one and then use
total expectation to
find the overall
expected length of time.
OK, so let's begin with
the first scenario.
The first scenario is that,
let's say, the first student
finished within five minutes.
So what does that mean in terms
of the definitions that
we've used?
That means T1 is less
than or equal to 5.
So if the first student took
less than five minutes, then
what happens?
Then we know that the
amount of time that
you'd need to take--
let's call that something
else.
Let's call that X. So X is the
random variable that we're
interested in, the time between
when the first student
comes and the second
student leaves.
This is the value that
we want to find.
Well we know that we're
guaranteed that there will be
a five-minute interval.
So first student will come,
and then the second person
will take over.
So we're guaranteed that the
first five minutes will be the
difference between when time
starts and when the second
student arrives.
And then, after that, it's just
however long the second
student takes, which is just
the expected value of T2.
And T2 is a exponential random
variable with mean 30.
So in this case, it's just 35.
So the first student doesn't
take very long.
Then we just get the five
minutes, that little buffer,
plus however long the second
student takes, which, on
average, is 30 minutes.
Now what is the probability
of this happening?
The probability of this
happening is the probability
that the first student takes
less than five minutes.
And here is where we use the CDF
that we wrote out earlier.
It's going to be 1 minus e
to the minus lambda t.
So in this case, t is five
and lambda is 1/30.
So it's minus 5/30 is
the probability.
All right, now let's consider
the second case.
The second case is that the
first student actually takes
longer than five minutes.
OK, so what happens
in that case?
Here's five minutes.
The first student came
to five minutes.
The second student arrived,
and the first
student is still going.
So he goes for some
amount of time.
And then whenever he finishes,
the second student continues.
So now the question is, what
is the total amount of
time in this case?
Well, you can think of it as
using the memoryless property.
This is where it comes in.
So the first five minutes, we
know that it was already taken
because we're considering the
second scenario, which we're
given that T1 is
greater than 5.
And so the question now is, if
we know that, how much longer
does it take?
How much longer past the
five-minute mark does the
first student take?
And by the memoryless property,
we know that it's as
if the first student
started over.
So there was no memory of the
first five minutes, and it's
as if the first student just
arrived also at the
five-minute mark and met
with the professor.
So past the five-minute mark,
it's as if you have a new
exponential random variable,
still with mean 30.
And so what we get is that,
in this case, you get the
guaranteed five minutes, and
then you get the memoryless
continuation of the first
student's appointment.
So you get another 30 minutes
on average because of the
memoryless property.
And then whenever the first
student finally does finish
up, the second student will
immediately take over because
he has already arrived.
It's past the five-minute
mark.
And then that second student
will take, again, on average,
30 more minutes.
So what you get is, in this
case, the appointment lasts 65
minutes on average.
Now what is the probability
of this case?
The probability of this case is
the probability that T1 is
greater than 5.
And now we know that that is
just the complement of this, 1
minus that.
So it's just e to
the minus 5/30.
So now we have both scenarios.
We have the probabilities of
each scenario, and we have the
expectation under
each scenario.
Now all that remains now is to
combine them using total
expectation.
So I really should have written
expectation of X given
T1 is less than or
equal to 5 here.
And this is expectation
of X given that T1 is
greater than 5.
So expectation of X overall is
the probability that T1 is
less than or equal to 5 times
the expectation of X given
that T1 is less than or equal to
5 plus the probability that
T1 is greater than 5 times the
expectation of X given that T1
is greater than 5.
And we have all four of
these pieces here.
so it's 35 times 1 minus e to
the minus 5/30 plus 65 times e
to the minus 5 5/30.
And it turns out that this
is approximately
equal to 60.394 minutes.
All right, so what
have we found?
We found that the original guess
that we had, if we just
had two meetings back to back,
was on average it would take
60 minutes.
It turns out that, because of
the way that things are set
up, because of the five minute
thing, it actually takes a
little longer than 60
minutes on average.
And why is that?
It's because the five sometimes
adds an extra
buffer, adds a little bit of
extra amount, because it would
have been shorter in this
scenario because, if the both
students had arrived on time,
then the second student would
have been able to pick up
right here immediately.
And so both appointments would
have ended sooner.
But because the second student
didn't arrive until five
minutes, there was some empty
space that was wasted.
And that's where you get you the
little bit of extra time.
So this is a nice problem just
to get some more exercise with
exponential random variables
and also nicely illustrates
the memoryless property, which
was a key points in order to
solve this.
And it also is nice because we
get to review a useful tool
that we've been using all course
long, which is to split
things into different scenarios
and then solve the
simpler problems and then
combine them up, for example
using total expectation.
So I hope that was helpful,
and see you next time.