In this lecture, we look in
some depth into various
properties of Poisson
processes.
These properties would be quite
hard to study if one
were to proceed just
analytically by
manipulating formulas.
However, by using memorylessness
and our
intuitive understanding of
what the Poisson process
really is, they become
quite simple.
And the mathematical
manipulations can be avoided
almost entirely.
We will start by arguing that
the sum of independent Poisson
random variables is Poisson.
But we will then establish the
much stronger statement that
if we merge two independent
Poisson processes, we, again,
obtain a Poisson process.
We will see that we can exploit
this fact to solve
some problems that would be
quite difficult otherwise.
Once more, intuitive reasoning
is the key.
Finally, we will spend some time
discussing a phenomenon
that goes under the name
of random incidence.
The Poisson process
has been running.
You show up at a certain time.
You look at the size of the
inter-arrival interval during
which you show up.
It turns out that this
inter-arrival interval that
you get to observe is
not a typical one.
It tends to be larger
than the typical
inter-arrival interval.
We will understand what exactly
is going on, build
some intuition, and realize
that this is a general
phenomenon that also shows up
in many other contexts.