In this unit, we more or less
repeat the entire development
in the previous unit, except
that we will now consider
continuous rather than discrete
random variables.
There are several reasons
for studying
continuous random variables.
The most important one is that
many quantities of interest,
for example, measurements of
time, length, or other
physical properties, are
naturally modeled as
continuous.
Another reason is that
continuous random variables
are sometimes easier to analyze,
because we can use
the machinery of calculus.
For example, integrals
are often easier to
evaluate than sums.
A last reason is that continuous
models often
provide a clean and simple
approximation of discrete models.
Our line of development will
parallel exactly what we did
for the discrete case.
We will describe the
distribution of continuous
random variables and talk
about expectations,
conditioning, and
independence.
As we will see, every formula
for the discrete case will
have a continuous counterpart.
The intuition will generally
be the same.
But there will be some
additional subtleties.
These are due to the fact that
in a continuous model any
particular value of a random
variable has zero probability.
And we will end this unit by
looking at variations of the
Bayes rule.
These will be the foundation
for our later study of the
subject of inference.
By the end of this unit, we will
have covered all of the
major concepts and formulas that
are needed to describe
and analyze random variables
of all types.