Hi.
In this problem, we're going to
get more practice working
with densities and also working
with conditional
densities by conditioning
on an event.
The density that we're given is
one for a random variable
X. And we're told that the
density is x over 4 when x is
between 1 and 3.
And otherwise, it's
equal to zero.
So here, I've drawn
out this density.
From 1 to 3, it's x over 4.
So it goes from 1/4 to
3/4, and outside
of that, it's zero.
And we're also given a
definition for an event, A,
which is the event that
this random variable
X is at least 2.
So think of it as here is
the line where it's 2.
A is the event that the random
variable is greater than or
equal to 2.
And now, in part (a),
we're asked to
find a bunch of things.
The first one is the expected
value of X. The expected
value, remember, the definition
is this integral.
You integrate x times
the density of X.
And the important thing here to
remember is that when you
plug this in, when you plug in
the density, which is x over
4, you need to remember
to correct the limits.
Because this density is only
valid from x from 1 to 3.
So instead of integrating from
minus infinity to infinity, we
only go from 1 to 3, because
outside of that range, this
integral is actually zero
because the density is zero.
So now it's just solving this
integral, which is x squared
over 4 from 1 to 3.
So what exactly is that?
That's going to give you 1/4.
And you integrate x squared.
That's 1/3 x cubed
from 1 to 3.
So that's 1/12 times 27 minus 1,
which gives you 26 over 12,
which you can also further
simplify, 13/6.
So that is our first answer.
And actually let's just check
that this kind of makes sense.
This is a little bit over 2,
so it's somewhere here.
And yes, that makes sense.
Because it makes sense
it's a little past 2.
If this were flat, if this were
uniform, then we know
that the expectation would
be exactly the
midpoint, which is at 2.
But it's actually skewed more
towards higher values of x.
So you would expect that the
expectation is actually to the
right of 2, a little
bit higher than 2.
So that seems to check out.
The next thing to calculate is
the probability of this event,
the probability of the event A,
which we could also write
as the probability that this
random variable is at least 2.
Now how do you calculate the
probability the random
variable is at least 2?
It's just a matter of
integrating the density.
And you integrate the density
starting from 2, because you
want it to be at least 2.
And you integrate it
all the way up.
In general, it would
be to infinity.
But we know that for values
of x greater than 3,
the density is 0.
So we actually just integrate
from 2 to 3.
Really, what we're doing
is we're just
calculating this part.
So we can just again plug
in what this is.
It's anywhere from 2 to
3 of the density.
In this range, this form will
hold, so it's x over 4.
And now that's going to give you
1/8 x squared from 2 to 3.
So it's 1/8 times 8.
Sorry, times 9 minus 4, which
gives you 5/8 as your answer.
And again, we can check that
this kind of makes sense.
The probability that the random
variable is at least 2
is 5/8, which is a little
bit more than half.
And again, we can compare
this to the case
where it would be uniform.
If it were uniform and flat,
then the probability that it's
greater than 2 would
be exactly half.
Because it's symmetric.
It's half on this side,
half on this side.
But because it's skewed, again,
more towards larger
values, you would expect the
probability that it's at least
2 to be a little bit
more than a half.
And the probably that it's less
than 2 would be a little
less than a half.
So that also checks out.
Now let's actually calculate the
next thing, which is the
conditional density of X given
the event A. So what does it
really mean?
It means now by conditioning on
A, we're saying that we're
in the universe where the
random variable is
actually at least 2.
So instead of focusing on the
original density, now we're
actually just in this
restricted universe
of just this part.
And now we want an updated
density for only this part.
And in general, what really
happens is you just take the
original density that held for
the entire random variable and
rescale it.
Because if you just
took this, it
wouldn't be a valid density.
Because we know that this
thing, this part of the
density, only integrates
to 5/8.
And you need a density
to integrate to 1.
So what do we do?
We take the original density and
rescale it so that it does
integrate to 1.
And what that amounts to is
really just taking the
original density and dividing
it by the probability of A,
which is the probability of
this portion of this.
And you see that that exactly is
the normalizing factor that
we need in order for this
to integrate to 1.
And again, we need to be a
little bit careful, because
this is only true when x is
within A, in other words, when
x is between 2 and 3.
And otherwise, it
would be zero.
Now we know what these
things are.
The original density is x
over four, and that was
valid from 1 to 3.
And we're in 2 to 3, so
that's still valid.
So it's x over four.
And then the probability of A we
calculated earlier is 5/8.
So when we divide that
by that, we get 8/5.
And so when you simplify this,
you get 2x over five.
And that becomes your
new density.
And we could actually also
plot out what this is.
And it would actually look
something like this.
It would be this portion
of the density.
So notice that 2/5 is the
slope as opposed to 1/4.
And really what we've done is
we've taken this and rescaled
it so that this trapezoid now
integrates actually to 1,
whereas this portion
of it would only
integrate it to 5/8.
Now for the last part of this
part (a), we're asked to find
a conditional expectation.
So conditioned on the event A,
what is the expectation of X?
Or put in other words, what is
the expectation of X given
that we know that
it's at least 2.
Well we know that when we
calculate expectations, the
general form is something like
this kind of integral.
But because we're conditioning
on A, we have to change the
density to the conditional
density.
So we integrate as before, x.
And we use the conditional
density,
which is 2x over five.
And now, we need to be careful,
because again, the
limits in general are minus
infinity to infinity.
But we need to write the right
ones, the ones that are valid
for this expression for the
conditional density.
So 2x over 5 is only
valid from 2 to 3.
So we integrate actually
from 2 to 3.
So what is this integral?
It's 2/5 times the integral
of 2 to 3 of x squared.
So it's 2/5 integral 1/3
x cubed from 2 to 3.
So it's going to give you
2/15 of 27 minus 8.
So the final answer
that you get--
this gives you 19 times
2 is 38 over 15.
And you can see that if
you look at this.
This is 2 and 8/15, which
is a little bit
more than 2 and 1/2.
And again, if we're in the
conditional world where x is
least 2 or effectively where
x is between 2 and 3.
And if, in this conditional
world, the distribution were
again uniform, you would
expect this conditional
expectation to be 2 and 1/2
exactly, the midpoint.
But because, just like before in
the unconditional world, in
the condition world, we still
had the case that it's skewed
more towards 3.
So because of that,
it's a little bit
more than 2 and 1/2.
So it's actually 38/15, which
you can again just do a quick
sanity check to make sure that
our answer makes sense.
Now one last part, part (b).
Now introduced a new random
variable Y. And we define it
as Y equal to X squared.
And we are asked to calculate
some things.
So first, let's calculate the
expected value of Y. Well, to
use the standard way, we would
have to calculate the pdf of
Y, and then use the
integral formula.
But in order to do that, we
would need the pdf of Y, but
we don't actually know
what that is.
But because Y is related to X,
we can actually just write it
in terms of expected
value of X squared
because Y is X squared.
And now, we use a formula.
The expectation of a function
of a random variable is the
same thing.
And so instead of writing just
X, we write the function of X.
So it's x squared times the
density of X. So that's the
general form.
And now let's actually
plug it in and see
what it actually is.
The density--
we go back to the original
case-- is x over 4.
So we get x cubed over 4.
And now also we need to
update the limits.
This density is only
valid from 1 to 3.
So we have to integrate
from 1 to 3.
So when we do this integral,
what do we get?
Well, we get x to the fourth
over 16 from 1 to 3, which
gives you 1/16.
And then you get 81--
3 to the fourth is 81--
minus 1.
So 80 over 16 is exactly 5.
So even though we don't know
exactly what the distribution
for Y is, we can use what we
know about X to calculate the
expectation of Y. Now the second
part is we want to find
the variance of Y. And again,
the usual formula is
expectation of Y squared
minus expectation
of Y quantity squared.
Now we already know
what this is.
Expectation of Y, we just
calculated, is 5.
But we also need to know
what the expectation
of Y squared is.
And we can use the same method
here, because Y squared is
just X to the fourth.
So expectation of Y
squared is just
expectation of X to the fourth.
And now we can use the exact
same sort of formula to
calculate what that is.
So we integrate x to the fourth
times the density of X.
We plug that in.
The density of X is x over
4, so this becomes x to
the fifth over 4.
And then, again, the limits we
need to be careful of goes
from 1 to 3.
So when we do have this
integral, we get x to the
sixth over 24 from 1 to 3,
which equals 91 over 3.
So the last part now is just
combining the pieces.
The variance of Y now is just
expectation of Y squared,
which is 91 over 3 minus
expectation of Y quantity
squared, which is 5
squared, is 25.
And that gives you 16 over
3 as your final answer.
So this problem really was kind
of a drill problem that
started out with giving you
a density and asked you to
calculate a variety of different
quantities related
to that density.
And then we also added another
wrinkle to a by conditioning
on an event and working with
a conditional density.
The last thing was coming up
with a related random variable
and using the original random
variable to help you calculate
quantities related to that
new random variable.
So we'll see you next time.