In this exercise, we'll be
looking at a problem,
so-called the birthday paradox,
where we have n
people and each person
has a random birthday
out of the 365 days.
And the probability we want to
measure is the probability of
the event that no two
birthdays coincide.
To set up the problem, we'll
define the sample space omega
as a set of all possible
birthday combinations.
Let's see how big that is.
Well, we have a collection
of n people.
And each person has
365 choices.
And therefore, the total
number choices for all
possible birthday combinations
will be this number raised to
the power n.
So this will be the size of
our sample space omega.
Now, out of the sample space
we'll look at all choices, all
combinations where no
two people have
exactly the same birthday.
To count that, we can start from
the first person, person
number one.
Well, this person has 365
choices because so far there
has not been any other
birthdays to
be conflicting with.
However, for the second person
we know that whatever the
first person chose, we
cannot choose the
same birthday again.
And so we're left with
364 choices.
Keep going like this, we get
363, and so on and so forth.
Until we reach the last person,
which will give us 365
minus n plus 1.
Since we've repeated this
process n times.
Now, looking at these two
numbers we know that the
probability of no two birthdays
coincide is equal to
the size of the event, which
is this problem here--
365 times 364, so on and so
forth, times 365 minus n plus
1, divided by the size of the
sample space, 365 raised to
the nth power.
Now, you might wonder how big
really is this probability?
Well, if we were to plot the
probability of having no two
birthdays coincide as a function
of the size of the
group n, where n goes from 0 all
the way to 80, we see that
the probability drops
very quickly.
In particular, if we were to
draw a line right here from
having 50 [percent]
chance of seeing no two
birthdays coincide.
We see that roughly around 23
we're already are seeing a
chance smaller than half.
If the group size is about 40
and the chance of having a
unique birthday for everyone
is only about 10%.
Now, here on the right we are
plotting the same probability
but with a different scaling.
So on the y-axis we're plotting
with respect to a
logarithmic scaling, showing
a finer granularity of
the value near zero.
Now we can see right here beyond
60 and the plot on the
left that we solved before,
you can barely
tell the value p-n.
So here if we were to track 60
around right here, we see that
the values start dipping below
1% and all the way to 10 to
the negative tenth.
So that's a tiny number, even
though we only have a
group of size 120.