In this segment, we will go
through a quite representative
application of the Bayes rule
to a situation that involves
two continuous random
variables.
The setting is as follows.
We start with two independent
random variables, and we get
to observe the sum of the two.
So for example, we might
have a signal.
That signal is transmitted
through some medium, and so it
is corrupted by noise, called
the noise Y. And we get to
observe Z. On the basis of the
observed value of Z, we would
like to say as much as we can
about the unknown signal, X.
How do we approach this?
Well, we will try to find the
conditional distribution of X
given the value z of the signal
that we have observed.
How do we calculate this
conditional distribution?
The setting here suggests
that we should be
using the Bayes rule.
So let's just write down the
formula for the Bayes rule
that we already have.
On the other hand, this formula
does not quite fit the
setting here.
This is the formula that would
be applicable if we were to
observe Y and try to say
something about X.
But here we're observing Z.
We're not observing Y. What
should we do?
It's very simple.
Just use the same formula.
But instead of having
y's, use z's.
So the formula takes this
equivalent form.
So this is what we want
to calculate--
the conditional distribution of
X given an observed value
of Z. In general, we will be
given the distribution of X.
So this would be a
known quantity.
But how about this?
We need the conditional
distribution of Z given X. In
other words, we essentially
need a model of how the
observations, z, are
constructed.
We're talking about a model of
this box that tells us, given
a value of X, what are
the properties of Z?
Suppose that instead, however,
all that we have in our hands
is the distribution of Y and the
knowledge that X and Y are
independent.
Somehow we need to use this
information to find the
distribution of Z. So
let us start working
towards this goal.
We can figure out what the
answer will be quite
intuitively if I tell you that
capital X takes a value of
little x, then in this
conditional universe, Z is
going to be just this
random variable.
And this is the same as the
random variable, capital Y,
except that a constant is added
to that random variable.
So Z is going to have the same
distribution as Y, except that
it gets shifted by an amount
of little X. So it has the
same distribution as
Y, except that the
distribution is shifted.
So instead of having an argument
z here, we will need
to have an argument z minus x.
So this corresponds to taking
the distribution of Y and
shifting it by x.
Another way to think about why
this argument, z minus x, here
is correct, notice that in
order for capital Z to be
equal to some little z, then
capital Y should be
equal to z minus x.
This is the value of Y that
makes the sum of x and y turn
out to be the same
as little z.
So intuitively, this is what
we would get for the
conditional density of Z. And
then we could just apply this
form of the Bayes rule.
It's instructive, though, to
re-derive this relation here
in a different and somewhat
more formal way.
So let us go through one
more derivation.
This time we will give an
argument that relies on CDFs.
And here's how it goes.
We will first find the
cumulative distribution
function of Z conditioned on X.
That is, we will attempt to
calculate this conditional
probability.
And then, since this is a
conditional CDF, we would then
take derivatives to find
conditional PDF.
This probability, by definition,
Z is X plus Y. So
we have this probability
conditioned on X
equal to little x.
But if we know that capital X
takes a value of little x,
then this capital X here can be
replaced just by little x.
And we obtain this
probability here.
Now, this is an expression,
which is a random variable,
because Y is random.
But little x is a number.
So Y is the only random variable
involved here.
Y is independent from X. So the
conditional distribution
given the value of capital X
should be the same as the
unconditional distribution.
And finally, we can rewrite
this event in this form--
the probability of capital
Y being less than or
equal to z minus x.
And we recognize that here
we have the cumulative
distribution of Y, but evaluated
at little z minus x.
Here we have the cumulative of
the conditional distribution
of Z given X.
We take the derivative of this
quantity to find the density
of the conditional distribution
of Z given X. And
that density has to be equal to
the derivative of this side
of the equation.
And the derivative here with
respect to z is just the
density of Y evaluated
at z minus x.
So we have verified, using a
second method, that this
formula here is correct.
So here's a summary of what
we have done so far.
We basically wrote down the
form of the Bayes rule.
And we wrote down how the
distribution of Z can be
expressed in terms of the
distribution of Y.
And so we now have available
an expression for this term
that appears in the numerator.
Now, let us look at the
concrete example.
Suppose that X and Y are
exponential random variables,
with a common parameter,
lambda.
How are we to think about
this situation?
We start at time zero.
We have a light bulb.
We wait until a light
bulb burns out.
And the time until a light
bulb burns out is
exponentially distributed with
some parameter lambda.
Then we start using
a new light bulb.
And that light bulb will also
remain alive for a random
amount of time.
Call it Y.
And at that time, the second
light bulb burns out as well.
The total amount of time that
has elapsed, we call it Z.
Somebody tells you the value of
Z. That's when the second
light bulb burned out.
And you're trying to say as
much as you can about the
value of X.
You know that X, the time of
the burn out of the first
bulb, was sometime before Z. But
you do not to know where
exactly in that interval
it's going to be.
So what we want to calculate is
a probability distribution
for X, which is going to be a
probability distribution on
this interval.
So let us now calculate.
In this example, we're
assuming that X is
exponential.
So the density of X takes this
form for x non-negative.
We're also told that Y is
exponential, with the same
distribution.
So we have the same expression
for the density of Y.
And now, we can fix some
z non-negative.
Only non-negative z's
are possible.
So we will try to calculate this
conditional PDF only for
non-negative z's.
And using the form of the Bayes
rule that we have, what
we got is, let's first put down
the denominator term.
And here we have lambda e
to the minus lambda x.
And this is valid when
x is non-negative.
And then we multiply with this
conditional density, which is
a conditional density of Y,
evaluated at z minus x.
And this is going to be
lambda e to the mines
lambda z minus x.
And this expression here is
valid when the density of Y
takes this form when the
argument is non-negative.
So it takes this form when the
The e argument is z minus x.
So this is valid when z minus
x is non-negative.
Or what is the same, it's valid
when x is less than or
equal to z.
So in this range, when x is
non-negative and x is less
than or equal to z, we
have this expression.
Now, we notice that we have a
term, e to the minus lambda x
here, and we have a similar term
here but with an extra
minus sign.
So these two terms will
cancel each other.
And what we're left with is
the following expression.
And this expression is valid
given the constraints that we
have imposed so far. z
is non-negative, x is
non-negative, and x is less
than or equal to z.
So it is valid when x and
z obey this condition.
And this is the form for the
conditional PDF of X if I tell
you the value of Z. This is
the form that it takes.
What's special about this PDF?
Remember that we have fixed
Z to a certain value.
And we're trying to describe
the likelihood of the
different values of
X. But there is no
dependence on x here.
So the PDF is constant
as a function of x.
And this means that if I tell
you the value of Z, then X is
going to have a uniform
conditional distribution on
this interval.
And this is quite interesting.
Essentially it tells
you the following.
Going back to our light bulb
example, if I tell you that
the second light bulb burned
out at this time, and I ask
you, when do you think the first
light bulb burned out,
you're going to tell me, I
really don't know, I have
complete ignorance.
Any time in this interval is,
in some sense, as likely as
any other time.
Now, this conclusion might seem
perhaps surprising or
unexpected.
But it becomes quite plausible
if you start thinking in terms
of coin tosses and the geometric
distribution.
To make a discrete time
analagous story, we could
think as follows.
We have here time that
is divided in slots.
And you keep tossing a coin
until heads is obtained for
the first time.
And this is a geometric
random variable.
Then you keep tossing again
until heads is obtained for
the second time.
So this Y is also going to be
a geometric random variable.
If I tell you that the second
heads showed up at this time
and I ask you, what do you think
about the first heads,
well, you're going to tell me,
I know that there was exactly
one head in the time
up to here.
But all slots are
equally likely.
The one head that we have may
have appeared in any one of
those previous slots.
And each one of those previous
slots has the same probability