In this three-lecture unit, we
introduce random processes or
stochastic processes as they
are sometimes called.
A random process is basically
a probabilistic phenomenon
that evolves in time.
An example would be the motion
of a balloon in the presence
of random wind gusts.
Another could be a sequence
of stock market prices.
Phenomena that evolve in time
can be quite complex even in a
deterministic setting.
But in this unit, we will focus
on a very simple class
of random processes, models that
describe arrivals that
occur over time and that
have no memory.
In discrete time, this
corresponds to carrying out an
independent trial at
each time slot.
And if the trial is
successful, we have an arrival.
This is the Bernoulli process.
In continuous time, things
are more complicated.
But we will develop a continuous
time analog of the
Bernoulli process, which is
called the Poisson process.
For the processes that we
introduce, we will study some
questions that are of
interest for any
type of arrival process.
For example, we will see how
we can find the probability
that there are exactly 10
arrivals during the next hour,
or the probability that the 10th
arrival happens within
two hours, or how to find the
distribution of the time
between the second and
the third arrival.
We will also go a little deeper
and consider what
happens when we manipulate
or combine
various arrival streams.
In some sense, all that we will
do in this unit will be
an application of skills
that we already have.
On the other hand, we will have
to rely heavily on an
intuitive understanding of these
processes, which is the
key to solving complex
problems.